<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Astrolabium vranicum generale A necessary and pleasaunt solace and recreation for nauigators in their long iorneying, containing the vse of an instrument or generall astrolabe: newly for them deuised by the author, to bring them skilfully acquainted with all the planets starres, and constellacions of the heauens ... In which, agreeable to the hipothesis of Nicolaus Copernicus, the starry firmament is appointed perpetually fixed and the earth and his horizons continually mouing from west towards the east once about euery 24 houres. Fraught also by new deuise with all such necessary supplements for iudiciall astrology, as Alkabitius &amp; Claudius Dariottus haue deliuered by their tables. Wherevnto for their further delight he hath anexed another inuention, expressing in one face the whole globe terrestriall; with the two great english voyages lately performed round about the world. Compyled by Iohn Blagraue of Reading Gentleman, the same wellwiller to the mathematicks. Anno. 1596.</title>
            <author>Blagrave, John, d. 1611.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1596</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 132 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 34 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A16195</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 3117</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S104607</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99840340</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99840340</idno>
            <idno type="VID">4837</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A16195)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 4837)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 175:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Astrolabium vranicum generale A necessary and pleasaunt solace and recreation for nauigators in their long iorneying, containing the vse of an instrument or generall astrolabe: newly for them deuised by the author, to bring them skilfully acquainted with all the planets starres, and constellacions of the heauens ... In which, agreeable to the hipothesis of Nicolaus Copernicus, the starry firmament is appointed perpetually fixed and the earth and his horizons continually mouing from west towards the east once about euery 24 houres. Fraught also by new deuise with all such necessary supplements for iudiciall astrology, as Alkabitius &amp; Claudius Dariottus haue deliuered by their tables. Wherevnto for their further delight he hath anexed another inuention, expressing in one face the whole globe terrestriall; with the two great english voyages lately performed round about the world. Compyled by Iohn Blagraue of Reading Gentleman, the same wellwiller to the mathematicks. Anno. 1596.</title>
                  <author>Blagrave, John, d. 1611.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[68] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Thomas Purfoot, for William Matts,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1596]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A-H⁴ I² .</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: The vranicall astrolabe.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Library of Congress.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Astrolabes --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Claire Tolan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Claire Tolan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:4837:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:4837:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Astrolabium <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ranicum Generale.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Neceſſary and Pleaſaunt ſolace and recreation for Nauigators in their long Iorneying, Containing the vſe of an Inſtrument or generall Aſtrolabe: Newly for them deuiſed by the Author, to bring them skilfully acquainted with all the Planets Starres, and conſtellacions of the Heauens: and their courſes, mouings, and apparences, called the (Vranicall Aſtrolabe.)</p>
            <p>In which, <hi>Agreeable to the</hi> Hipotheſis <hi>of</hi> Nicolaus Coper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicus, the Starry Firmament is appointed perpetually fixed, and the earth and his Horizons continually mouing from Weſt towards the Eaſt once about euery 24 houres.</p>
            <p>Fraught alſo by new deuiſe with all ſuch neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary ſupplements for Iudiciall Aſtrology, as ALKA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>BITIVS &amp; CLAVDIVS DARIOTTVS haue deliuered by their Tables.</p>
            <p>Wherevnto for their further delight he hath anexed ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther inuention, expreſsing in one face the whole Globe terreſtriall; with the two great engliſh voyages lately performed round about the world.</p>
            <p>Compyled by IOHN B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>GRAVE of Reading Gentleman, the ſam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> well willer to the Mathematicks. Anno. 1596.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Printed by Thomas Purfoot, for William Matts.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:4837:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:4837:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>¶ To the Right Honorable-Lord,</hi> the Lord Charles Haward, Baron of Effingham, Lord high Admirall of England, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight Honorable, for ſo much as my ſelfe, with the whole progeny of our name, haue beene alwayes exceedingly bounde, Next to the Right Honorable our good Lord the Lord Burleigh, Lord high Treaſurer of England, Vnto the late right Honorable Sir Fraunces Knolles the elder Knight, Treaſurer of her highneſſe moſt honourable houſehold, deceaſed, in regard of their ſinceare iuſtice, and charitable reſpect of moſt iniurious and wicked practiſes heretofore vehemently proſecuted a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt vs, for no leſſe then the liuing we all poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed. Both whome therefore (vnder your Lordships good fauour) I can not, but in all my beſt indeuours, during life remember, Not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getting as in duty I am bound, the Right Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable Sir William Knolles Knight, now Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troller of her Maieſties ſayd moſt honorable houſehold, and ſuch other his right worship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
<pb facs="tcp:4837:3"/> and honorable minded off-ſpring, as ſtill re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine our good fauorers. Amongſt whom, the right Worship. M. Robert Knolles more then a yeare paſſed of his accuſtomed kindnes aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſed me, that your L. I know not by what meanes, vnderſtanding of my indeuors in theſe Mathematick Sciences, was pleaſed to take fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther notice of me by my perſonall preſence. For the which, as the time hath not bin fitting by reaſon of your L. moſt ſerious important &amp; honorable imployments, aſwell to the ſeas as o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe this yeare 1596 well knowne to the whole world. So haue I bin willing to catch hold of the opportunity thereof ſo far: as in the meane time to hammer out (if ſelfliking deceiue me not) a rare piece of Mathematicke ſtuffe, to bring vnto your L. view, together with my ſelf: tending both to the profit and pleaſure of all worthy english Gent. that either addict them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to contemplacion at home, or to Marine traueyles abroad. Which if it may receiue fauo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable allowance at your good L. hands, I shall thinke my ſelfe ſuffiicie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly defended againſt all ignorant or maligna<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t detractors, and be the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hereafter encouraged to go forwards with like matters. Thus praying vnto God for the long preſeruacion of your Honour, I ceaſe.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Lordſhips moſt humble, Iohn Blagraue.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:4837:3"/>
            <head>To the curteous Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Entle Reader, the eares of my guilty conceit being continually troubled with ſuch a noyſe and clamor for my (Organum Vranicum,) and the ſecond part of my Mathematicall Iewell, ſo long and largely promiſed, as the greedy Auditors are woont to make at a Stage-play: calling, Come away howe, with boyes thro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing vollyes of ſtones ratling at the gates of my otherwiſe buiſied imployments, for ſtaying ſo long: Maketh me heere in haſte (God graunt to your liking) to come vp the Stage, with a little, but rare piece of Mathematicke Muſickly pleaſure, not impertinent to the matter to be acted: to ſtay your langui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing expectations, both woorth the acceptacion (which I dare boldly aduouch againſt the doggedſt detractor that ſhall contradict) and ſufficient to entertaine the time vntill Midſomer or Michelmas Terme at the fartheſt, when as (if God permit) the ſtately Comedy of Queene Vranya hir Pageants, ſhall abundantly offer themſelues to your pleaſant viewe, Sollace your ſelues I pray you heerewith the whiles, and be bold with me if in any thing you doubt. You ſhall haue me God willing once euery Terme in London ready to your wiſh, at a poore lodging within Maiſter Greenes Wharfe neere vnto Charing Croſſe: and at Maiſter Ralfe Iackſons at the ſigne of the Swan in S. Paules Churchyard, or at Maiſter William Matts Stationer, at the ſigne of the Plough, ouer a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt S Dunſtons Church in Fleeteſtreete, who hath the Impreſſion of this Booke, you ſhall euer know whether I be at any time in the Citty: With whome, I haue taken order to furniſh with theſe In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments and their ſupplements any that ſhall want them.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:4837:4"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> The Contents of the Chapters of this worke, of the Vranicall Aſtrolabe.</head>
            <list>
               <item>Cap. 1. OF the partes of this new Aſtrolabe.</item>
               <item>Cap. 2. Of the Celeſtiall proiectinent in this new Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>labe, and how the longitudes and latitudes of the Starres are thereby had.</item>
               <item>Cap. 3. Of certaine abbreuiated tearmes or phraſes of arte appertayning to this new Aſtrolabe.</item>
               <item>Cap. 4. How to place Carects of the Planets in this Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>labe to ſerue there the whole weeke after.</item>
               <item>Cap. 5. How by this new Aſtrolabe to finde the true place of the ☉ perpetually.</item>
               <item>Cap. 6. How to rectifye the true place of the Sunne to all places of the world.</item>
               <item>Cap. 7. How to rectifye the place of the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> or of any other Planet, to any other Meridian.</item>
               <item>Cap. 8. How to know the declinacion and right aſcenſcion of any Planet, fixed Starre, or point of the heauens, and their degree of Culminacion.</item>
               <item>Cap. 9. How to finde the true Meridian in any Countrey by helpe of this Aſtrolabe.</item>
               <item>Cap. 10. How to attaine the latitude or Poles Eleuacion in any countrey vnknowne, and to chooſe out the Verticall point in the noone-line, the Horizontall point in the North line, and the Zenith line ſeruing thereunto.</item>
               <item>Cap. 11. How to take the Meridian altitude of the Sunne or any Planet or Starre, and thereby to get the latitude in any Countrey.</item>
               <item>Cap. 12. How to know what day of the yeare it were if it were forgotten.</item>
               <item>Cap. 13. How to know what it is a clocke at any time either night or day, by the Sunne, Planets, or Starres.</item>
               <item>Cap. 14. Another more eaſy way to finde the houre by the Starres.</item>
               <item>Cap. 15. Another eaſy way by the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g>.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:4837:4"/>
               <item>Cap. 16. How to know the Meridian altitude of the ☉, or any other Planet, Starre, or point of the heauens in any Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, and what houre of the day or night any of them ſhall culminate or come to the Meridian of that place.</item>
               <item>Cap. 17. How to know the houre of Sunne-riſing and ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, and the length of the day and night, together with his oblique aſcenſion, and his difference of aſcenſcion any day in the yeare.</item>
               <item>Cap. 18. To know the houre of riſing or ſetting of any other Planet, Starre, or point in the heauens, and their diurnall and nocturnall arches, and their oblique aſcenſcions and difference of aſcenſcions in any countrey.</item>
               <item>Cap. 19. How to ſet particular degrees on the Almicantiſer for any perticular latitude.</item>
               <item>Cap. 20. How to know the Amplitude of riſing or ſetting of the Sunne or Starres.</item>
               <item>Cap. 21. To know what Starres do neuer riſe or ſet in any latitude, and which do once a day touch the Zenith point, or Horizontall point.</item>
               <item>Cap. 22. To know any day and houre what Starres or points in the heauens are in or neere the Meridian, or do riſe or ſet in any latitude.</item>
               <item>Cap. 23. How to know the houre, diſtance of any Planet, Starre, or point of the heauens from the Meridian, any day and yeare propoſed in any latitude.</item>
               <item>Cap. 24 How to know the height of the Sunne or of any other Planet or Starre for any houre of the day any yeare in any latitude.</item>
               <item>Cap. 25. How you ſhall moſt eaſily learne to know all the conſtellacions and Starres in the element it ſelfe.</item>
               <item>Cap. 26. Of the 4 Cardines, and the ſundry riſing and ſetting of the fixed Starres with the Planets.</item>
               <item>Cap. 27. Of the 12 houſes, and ſetting the Figure.</item>
               <item>Cap. 28. Of the aſpects of the Planets and Starres, and how to finde them.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:4837:5"/>
               <item>Cap. 29. A new deuiſe of the Author to get the Planetary houres moſt eaſily in all latitudes, and of their Lordes regnant.</item>
               <item>Cap. 30. How you ſhall know to ſet forwards and back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards any of the fixed Starres vnto their true places for any ages paſt, or to come.</item>
               <item>Cap. 31. How by helpe of this Aſtrolabe to get the longitude and latitude of any Planet, yea, or of any Starre or Comet ſeene.</item>
               <item>Cap. 32. A ready way by helpe of this Aſtrolabe heereafter to obſerue the motions of Comets.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:4837:5"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Astrolabium <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ranicum Generale.</hi> Heere followeth the booke of the vſe of the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ranicall Astrolabe,</hi> Newly deuiſed by Iohn Blagraue of Reading, Gentleman.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>Cap. 1. ¶ Of the partes of this new Aſtrolabe.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His <hi>Aſtrolabe</hi> hath three generall partes, that is to ſay, the <hi>Celeſtiall,</hi> the <hi>Zenitfer</hi> with his <hi>Curſor,</hi> and the <hi>Almicantifer</hi> with his <hi>Pointer.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I call that part the <hi>Celeſtiall</hi> heere, which in other Aſtrolabes is called the <hi>Mate<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> of which I will largely ſpeake in the next Chap.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Zenitfer</hi> beeing but as a playne rule of one ynch bredth, mooueth vpon the <hi>Celeſtiall</hi> in ſtead of a <hi>Reete</hi> vſed in other Aſtrolabes: and hath a circular Lymbe thereto annexed neere vnto the Centre, which I call the <hi>Circulus horarius,</hi> or houre circle, with the 24. houres, and their partes thereon, as you ſee. Neither is it materiall of what quantity that houre circle or lymbe be of, ſo it be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centricke to the Aſtrolabe, and placed ſo, that it hide feweſt Starres in his moouing. And for ſeruice of this circle, there is written at the vpper end of this Zenitfer <hi>Meridies,</hi> and at
<pb facs="tcp:4837:6"/> the lower end <hi>Media nox,</hi> and therefore the fiduciall line thereof from the Centre vpwards to <hi>Meridies,</hi> is generally called the <hi>Noone line,</hi> the other part from the Centre downe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes vnto <hi>Media nox</hi> the <hi>North line.</hi> Then hath it 90 <hi>Zenith lines</hi> ſtanding in aſcents one aboue another like Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan pipes, in ſtead of the 90 generall <hi>Horizons</hi> before time vſed, iſſuing or growing out of the 90 <hi>Zenith points:</hi> for the loweſt points of theſe 90 lines neereſt vnto the centre vnto which their numbers are ſet from 0 to 90, do repreſent the true <hi>Zenithes</hi> of all places. Theſe 90. <hi>Zenith lines,</hi> are by certaine thwart curued lines parted euery one into 90 vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euen parts, of which ſome run out infinitely, and thoſe partes I call the <hi>Altitude rootes,</hi> or the <hi>Almicantare rootes,</hi> and for breuities ſake ſometimes <hi>Rootes</hi> without any addition. Theſe <hi>Rootes</hi> do helpe vs to generall <hi>Almicantares,</hi> or circles of Altitude for any Latitude by a rare deuiſe by me firſt found out. They are numbered on the outer ſide of the <hi>Zenitfer</hi> from their extreame points inwards towards their ſayd <hi>Zenith points,</hi> ending at them with 90. Alſo to the Fiduciall line of this <hi>Zenitfer</hi> is anexed a ſcale, in which are planted the Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diall degrees of the proiectement on both ſides of the Scale, becauſe they require double numbering for ſundry purpoſes. And of thoſe which bound on the Fiduciall line, thoſe at the noone line are numbered from the Equinoctiall interſection both waies, <hi>vz.</hi> towards <hi>Meridies,</hi> as farre as the <hi>Zenithfer</hi> will giue leaue, which are about 36, and towards the Centre, ending there at 90. which 90 radiall degrees of the noone line towards the Centre do ſerue (with the other 36) to deſcry the declinations of the fixed Starres and Planets, but chiefely they ſerue for the 90 Zenithes which appertaine to the 90 generall Horizons, and for diſtinction ſake I call them the 90 <hi>Verticall points,</hi> and they exactly anſwere vnto the 90. lower ends of the 90 <hi>Zenith lines,</hi> which before I called the 90 <hi>Ze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nith points,</hi> in ſo much that the fiduciall line of the <hi>Curſor</hi> in his moouing, cutteth the <hi>Zenith point,</hi> and the <hi>Verticall point</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4837:6"/> of any latitude both at once. The other <hi>Radiall</hi> degrees in the <hi>North line,</hi> are numbred from the centre towards <hi>Media nox,</hi> ending at the Equinoctials interſexion therewith at 90, and do ſerue for the 90 interſections of the 90 generall <hi>Horizons</hi> therewith, and therefore I call them the 90 <hi>Horizontall points.</hi> And of thoſe radyall degrees which bound on the other ſide of the Scale, which indeede ſerue to the getting of the 12 houſes generally, as is ſhewed in the 27 Cap. The Norther 90 towards <hi>Media nox</hi> are numbred inwards to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Centre, ending there at 90 contrary to the former. And the Souther of thoſe radiall degrees are numbred from the Centre outwards towards <hi>Meridies</hi> two to one, as farre as they will go, (that is to ſay) euery 10 make but 5, and theſe do ſerue but in ſtead of rootes to the other, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I call them the <hi>Domifieng rootes.</hi> Alſo there adioyneth vnto the Radiall ſcale of the North line betweene the centre and the Zenith lines a certaine ſcale of ſlope lines numbered in the middeſt, beginning but from 60 and ending at the centre with 90, which I call the <hi>Domifieng Scale,</hi> for that the two extreames of euery of thoſe ſlope lines, do help to get 8 of the 12 houſes in that latitude, whoſe number it ſheweth, as in the 27 Cap. is manifeſted: and vnto the outer edge of this <hi>Domifieng ſcale,</hi> are alſo anexed part of the former ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diall degrees, all hauing relacion to them on the North line. Then hath this <hi>Zenitfer</hi> a certaine runner or <hi>Curſor,</hi> whoſe fiduciall line alwayes runneth exactly ſquare to the fiduciall line of the <hi>Zenitfer.</hi> And at the common meeting of both thoſe fiduciall lines, this <hi>Curſor</hi> hath iointed vnto him a kinde of Labell or looſe ſcale, which I call the <hi>Almicantifer,</hi> who to ſupply the generall vſe of the <hi>Almicantares,</hi> hath no manner of matter on him but another <hi>Curſor,</hi> which I call a <hi>Pointer.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But now for any man that deſireth to haue this Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>labe more particularly commodious for one latitude, <hi>vz.</hi> for the countrey or place of his abode, then ſhall he haue a kinde
<pb facs="tcp:4837:7"/> of Reete or moouer made, carying a circle or limbe of houres of equall diametre to the <hi>Celeſtiall,</hi> and within it the <hi>Horizon</hi> circle of that place particularly deſcribed after <hi>Stophlerus,</hi> and graduated into his 360 proſpectiue degrees, as in the fourth booke 4. Cap. of my Iewell is taught, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the arches diſtinguiſhing the 12 houſes, as in <hi>Stoph. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>propo.</hi> 6. is taught, writing to each houſe his number and ſignifications. And vnto the noone-line furni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed with the former radiall degrees, numbred from the <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rizon</hi> circle, into twiſe 90. both ending at the <hi>Verticall</hi> point, you ſhall neede to annexe but only one of the 90 Zenith lines, <hi>vz.</hi> that which ſerueth to your latitude and his rootes, with the <hi>Curſor:</hi> Neither neede your <hi>Almicantifer</hi> haue his ſliding pointer, but in ſtead thereof, the particuler degrees of altitude ſeruing to that latitude, which are compounded of his 90 Zenith rootes, and the 90 radiall degrees in the North line, as in the 19 Cap. is taught, all which ſhall better appeare by ſuch Aſtrolabes as I meane to ſet abroade ready furniſhed.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>Cap. 2. ¶ Of the Celeſtiall proiectment in this new Aſtrolabe, and how the longitudes and latitudes of the Starres are thereby had.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Eedleſſe it is to ſtand vpon the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brication, or long particularizing of this Inſtrument or his partes, ſince they are but the <hi>Copernician</hi> repreſentation of the conſtellations fixed, and the 90 generall <hi>Horizons</hi> moouing.</p>
               <p>The Fixed part which in other Aſtrolabes is called the <hi>Mater,</hi> I call for breuities ſake the <hi>Celeſtiall,</hi> For that in it I haue
<pb facs="tcp:4837:7"/> proſpectiuely proiected the Globe Celeſtiall, that is to ſay, the Globe of the fixed Starres, with the <hi>Zodiack,</hi> and his North Pole (marked with <hi>D</hi>) the Images of each conſtel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, and the Starres appertaining, in ſuch ſort as in the Globe they are vſuall, with each fift circle of Longitude and Latitude of the Zodiacke, Euery ſixe of thoſe fiues of the Longitude including a ſigne in the heauens, being 12 in the whole, which 12 are diſtinguiſhed with twiſted lines ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what bigger from the reſt, and vnto them neere vnto the Limbe are written the names of the 12 Signes as they paſſe in order, <hi>Aries, Taurus, &amp;c.</hi> together with their natures and quallities. Alſo, thoſe three Signes of the watry triplicitie are filled vp with waues, and the three fiery with flames, and the three earthy with bigge prickes, and the three ayry left white. Then are there ſeuen ſeuerall magnitudes of Starres, each bigger and brighter then other, whoſe faſhions are ſet downe with their numbers in the Signe ♊ before the breſt of <hi>Orion,</hi> by which they are eaſily heerein deſcryed. The excentricke circle <hi>Orbs</hi> or Lymbe, lying wholy within it, is the Zodiacke deuided into his 12 Signes by the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayd 12 mayſter circles of longitude, and euery Signe into his 30 proſpectiue degrees. Alſo the degrees are made with, diuers diſtinguiſhments, for the <hi>Gradus maſculini, feminini, lucidi, tenebroſi, vacui, fumoſi, puteales, fortunam augentes, &amp; debilitantes,</hi> all which are ſufficiently to be deſcryed by the two <hi>Directoria Zodiaci</hi> there placed. Then is there a little within the Zodiacke a rowe of Carecters of the Planets pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced at euery 10 circle of longitude, ſignifying the faces of the Planets, and likewiſe another rowe without the Zodiacke at the beginning of the termes of the Planets, euery face and terme continuing vnto the carect next him in <hi>ſequens</hi> of the Zodiacke, all which will better appeare, if you ioyne vnto this booke <hi>Claudius Dariot</hi> his introduction to the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Starres, which by good hap is now newly im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>printed in engliſh together with this, and a ſecond part there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with,
<pb facs="tcp:4837:8"/> which at the firſt impreſſion was omitted. And ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally you muſt note and remember well, that the very outer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt circle of this Zodiacke, is the clipticke circle, within which is contayned the North-halfe or Hemiſpheere of all the Starres and Conſtellacions in the heauens, and without it ſo many of the South Starres and Conſtellacions, as the proiectment would admit. Then is there alſo lying within this Aſtrolabe a blacke concentricke circle, repreſenting the <hi>Aequinoctiall</hi> circle, and proiector of this worke, but without any diuiſions, becauſe they are better ſupplyed by the limbe. Alſo there is a ſcale of the radiall degrees, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this proiectement is made, placed at the maſter circle of longit. beginning the Signe ♋ numbred from the Equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noctiall both wayes, which Equinoctiall cutteth the ſayde eclipticke circle in the pointes <hi>B</hi> and <hi>C</hi> beginning ♈ and ♎, and thoſe points are called the two <hi>Aequinoctiall Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſectiones</hi> which do mooue vppon the poles of the <hi>Zodiacke</hi> backwards, or <hi>in precedentia,</hi> of the Signes euery 67 yeares almoſt a degree equally: carying about with them all the foreſayde circles of Longitude and Latitude, leauing the Starres ſtocke ſtill in their places, By which meanes it commeth to paſſe, that although the fixed Starres haue no manner of motion at all, yet they ſeeme from time to time to haue gone as is ſayd euery 67 yeares almoſt a degree for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, as the auncient Aſtronomers thought: where as in very deede (as <hi>Copernicus</hi> ſheweth) the <hi>Zodiacke</hi> and all his circles do ſlide ſo much backwards from them: And by reaſon this ſliding backe of the <hi>Aequinoctiall</hi> points, is as I haue ſayd performed on the poles <hi>D</hi> and his oppoſite of the clipticke, therefore it commeth to paſſe that the fixed Starres could thereby neuer change theyr Latitudes, but keepe the ſame Latitudes as euer they did. This ſliding backe, is called <hi>Preceſſio Aequinoctiorum,</hi> of which wee will in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treate more in the 30 Cap. And now will returne to this proiectement: In which it is very eaſye to imagine euery
<pb facs="tcp:4837:8"/> ſquare into fiue equall partes, and ſo thereby to knowe the Longitude and Latitude of any Starre therein ſufficient for any common vſe. As for example, the great Starre in the left foote of <hi>Orion,</hi> placed in the Signe ♊, if you imagin the ſpaces betweene each fiue circles of Longitude and Lati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude deuided into fiue partes, then ſhall you conceaue that the middle pricke of this Starre is heere in longitude about 9 degrees 30 minut. of ♊, and in latitude South from the clipticke circle about ſome 31 degrees 30 min. and ſo for any of the reſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>Cap. 3. ¶ Of certaine abbreuiated termes or phraſes of arte, appertayning to this new Aſtrolabe.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Ecauſe this Aſtrolabe is newly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſed and his tackling, much diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring from all other heeretofore both in faſhion, vſe, and names, I haue therefore heere thought good to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe certaine abbreuiated termes thereunto fitly appertaining, leaſt otherwiſe ſuch long iteracion of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers circumſtances as at euery time I mention them I ſhould be driuen to vſe, ſhould make my writings yrkeſome, and my booke ouer long. Which tedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes to auoyde, I haue further not onely couched diuers precepts and propoſitions almoſt into euery Chapter, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo incorporated the examples with them, yet in another let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, to the end you may if you liſt firſt reade ouer euery Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, leauing out the example euen as though it were not. And if you vnderſtand it ſo, it is well, if not, then reade it, and practiſe the example withall.</p>
               <list>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4837:9"/>
                  <item>Are all one in ſignification, but in this practiſe the one is taken in the noone line, the other in the Zenith line of the place, as in the 1. Cap. is noted.
<list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>The Verticall point,</hi> 
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>The Zenith point,</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Horizontall point,</hi> is alwayes that radiall degree of the north line, reckned from the centre which is equall to the latitude, or poles eleuation, explaned both in the 1. &amp; 10. Cap.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Zenith line,</hi> explaned in the 1. and 10. Cap.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The North</hi> and <hi>South degrees,</hi> are the 90. radiall degrees on the noone and north lines, on each ſide of the <hi>Verticall point</hi> explaned in the 10. Cap.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Eaſt</hi> and <hi>Weſt Hemiſpheares</hi> are thus, in euery con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitucion of this Aſtrolabe, the Fiduciall line of the <hi>Zenitfer</hi> deuideth the <hi>Celeſtiall,</hi> in halfe of which, that halfe Eaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards of the noone line towards vi. of the clocke in the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, I call the <hi>Eaſt Hemiſphere,</hi> the other halfe I call the <hi>Weſt Hemiſpheare.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>To play the Almicantifer</hi> in the Eaſt or Weſt <hi>Hemiſphere</hi> is as much to ſay, as to keepe him moouing wholy on the Eaſt, or Weſt ſide of the noone line accordingly.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>To apply the pointer</hi> to any Starre or Carect, is to leade the <hi>Zenitfer,</hi> and the <hi>Almicantifer</hi> about, till you may cauſe the <hi>Apex</hi> of the pointer to touch the carect, or the middle prick of the Starre.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>To labell the Hower</hi> to the Sunne or Starres, or them to the hower. explaned in the 13. Cap.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>To prepare the Zenitfer</hi> to any altitude. explaned in the 13. Cap.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>To prepare the Zenitfer</hi> to the <hi>Horizon,</hi> is explaned in the 17. Cap.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>To prepare the Almicantifer to a particular latitude,</hi> expla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the 19. Cap.</item>
               </list>
               <p>Alſo when it is ſayd, <hi>Place the Zenitfer, or Labell to any Planet, Starre, or point:</hi> it is meant, that you muſt place the ſiduciall lines thereunto, and that with relation to the centre.
<pb facs="tcp:4837:9"/> The complement of any degree is ſo much as it lacketh of 90. degrees.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, you ſhall vnderſtand, that in writing of this whole worke, my meaning was that euery man ſhould haue the fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niture of this Aſtrolabe (whether generall or particular) made of mettall, as commonly the furnitures of Globes are, For which, if any man ſhall repaire or ſend vnto me either by him ſelfe, or by Maiſter <hi>Matts</hi> the bookeſeller, dwelling at the ſigne of the Plough ouer againſt <hi>S. Dunſtons</hi> Church in Fleet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreete, who ſhall eaſily at all times ſend any letter or notice weekely vnto me by our Carryers, I will take ſuch order that he ſhall haue them as reaſonably done as may be. And to the ende that euery man may ſee how it ought to be made in mettall, I haue cauſed a rude patterne of each furniture in mettall to remaine with the ſayd Maiſter <hi>Matts.</hi> Notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, for ſuch as will not go to that little charge, I haue vpon better aduiſement cauſed the <hi>Zenitfer</hi> and <hi>Curſor</hi> to be imprinted with the <hi>Aſtrolabe,</hi> to be ſet either on paſtboord, or cuttlers ſcale to ſerue the turne: But in ſtead of the <hi>Almi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cantifer</hi> and his <hi>pointer,</hi> then muſt they vſe a thred and pearle, which ſhall do in a manner as well, for the pearle ſhall in all actions ſupply the ſteede of the <hi>pointer.</hi> And in ſteede of the ledge of braſſe in the beginning of the next Cap. mentioned, he may haply cauſe a breadth of lantornes horne to be riuetted ouer the <hi>Zodiacke,</hi> vnder which to place the Carects of the Planets, made of paſte-boord, quilles, or ſuch like.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>Cap. 4. ¶ How to place Carects of the Planets in this Aſtrolabe, to ſerue there the whole weeke after.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>OR this purpoſe you ſhall take a paire of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe, and pitch his one foote in the line begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning ♑ at 25 degrees from the-cliptickes pole, and extend the other in the ſame line vnto 7 de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees
<pb facs="tcp:4837:10"/> of latitude, and with that quantity deſcribe a blinde circle, on wh ch blinde circle ſo made you ſhal place a narrow hoope of lattin braſſe, riuetted on the <hi>Mater</hi> with 4 or 8 riuets at the moſt, with ſo many thin bouiſters vnder euery riuer, that the hoope preſſe not hard on the <hi>Mater,</hi> to the end that you may thruſt vnder it ſome 9 Carrects, 5 of them carying two <hi>Apices</hi> or pointers ioynted together, made all of thin mettall and very narrow, <hi>vz.</hi> 7 for the 7 Planets, and 2 for the Moones <hi>cap,</hi> and <hi>Cau. draconis,</hi> there to ſticke very faſt till they be weekely remooued, and let one of the <hi>Apices</hi> of each Carect be leſſe and ſleighter then the other, which you ſhall better vnderſtand by ſuch as I haue, and ſhall cauſe to be ready made to your hand then by manifold words.</p>
               <p>Theſe things prouided for, then at the beginning of any weeke of any yeare propoſed (<hi>Admit for the beginning of the firſt Sunday in March, which ſhall be Anno Domini</hi> 1598.) you ſhall then by my <hi>Organum Vranicum,</hi> which God wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, long before that day ſhall be extant, or by your <hi>Epheme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris,</hi> or other Tables of the Planets motions get the true pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of euery of the 7 Planets as well in Longitude as Lati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, and of the ☊ and ☋, <hi>(which on the ſaid Sunday being the</hi> 5 <hi>day of March</hi> 1598 <hi>you ſhall by Stadius his Epheme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rides, finde the</hi> ☉ <hi>to be</hi> 25 <hi>degrees</hi> 3 <hi>minutes in</hi> ♓, <hi>the</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> 2 <hi>degrees</hi> 40 <hi>minutes in</hi> ♋, <hi>hir Latitude then</hi> 4 <hi>degrees</hi> 30 <hi>min. North,</hi> ♄ 2. <hi>degr.</hi> 32 <hi>min. in</hi> ♎, <hi>in Latit.</hi> 2 <hi>degr.</hi> 44 <hi>min. North,</hi> ♃ 9 <hi>degr.</hi> 26 <hi>min. in</hi> ♊, <hi>in latit. South</hi> 0 38 <hi>min.</hi> ♐ <hi>in</hi> ♐, 1 <hi>degr.</hi> 39 <hi>min. in</hi> ♋, <hi>in lat.</hi> 2 <hi>degr.</hi> 13 <hi>min. North,</hi> ♀ 10 <hi>degr.</hi> 51 <hi>min. in</hi> ♉, <hi>in latit.</hi> 1 <hi>degr.</hi> 40 <hi>min. North,</hi> ☿ 4 <hi>degr.</hi> 26 <hi>min. in</hi> ♈, <hi>in latit.</hi> 2 <hi>degr.</hi> 58 <hi>min. North,</hi> ☊ 6. <hi>degr.</hi> 16 <hi>min. in</hi> ♓, <hi>the</hi> ☋ <hi>is alwaies oppoſite, vz.</hi> 6 <hi>degr.</hi> 16 <hi>min. in</hi> ♍, <hi>both which, and likewiſe the</hi> ☉ <hi>neuer haue latitude.)</hi> Which places you ſhall reddily finde out in this <hi>Aſtrolabe,</hi> by meanes of the circles of Longit. and Latit. thereon deſcribed, and vnto them ſet the chiefe <hi>Apex</hi> of each Planets Carect accordingly, carefully prouiding that you ſet the <hi>Apex</hi> of the ☉ his Carect
<pb facs="tcp:4837:10"/> iuſtly to the-clipticke circle mentioned in the 2 Cap. at his exact degree and minute, becauſe he hath no Latitude, and he is the Chiefetaine guide in all our worke following, and ſo likewiſe the ☊ and ☋, as for all the reſt, you ſhall place their apices vnto the paralell circle, expreſſing his Latitude at his degree of Longitude reckoned in the ſame paralell by help of the circles of longitude: Which done, you ſhall then againe either by your <hi>Vranicum</hi> or <hi>Ephemerides,</hi> get in like ſort the places of them all for the beginning of the next Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day following (<hi>which will be the</hi> 12 <hi>day of March that yeare</hi> 1598. <hi>the</hi> ☉ <hi>then being</hi> 1 <hi>degr.</hi> 57 <hi>min. in</hi> ♈, <hi>the</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> 27 <hi>deg.</hi> 8 <hi>min. in</hi> ♍, <hi>hir latit.</hi> 1 <hi>degr.</hi> 47 <hi>min. North,</hi> ♄ 1 <hi>degr.</hi> 56 <hi>min. in</hi> ♎, ♃ 10 <hi>degr.</hi> 24 <hi>min. in</hi> ♊, ♐ 4 <hi>degr.</hi> 10 <hi>min. in</hi> ♋, ♀ 16 <hi>degr.</hi> 46 <hi>min. in</hi> ♉, ☿ 28 <hi>degr.</hi> 32 <hi>min. in</hi> ♓, ☊ 5 <hi>degr.</hi> 54 <hi>min. in</hi> ♓, <hi>as for their latitudes they alter little or nothing in</hi> 6 <hi>or</hi> 7 <hi>dayes.</hi>) and to thoſe places accordingly ſought in this Aſtrolabe, you ſhall ſet the petty <hi>Apices</hi> of each Carect. There ſhall they ſerue you for all that weeke to ſinguler ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects, and preſently you may note thus much, that if the petty <hi>Apex</hi> happen to be thus placed in <hi>ſequens</hi> of the <hi>Zodiacke</hi> from the chiefe <hi>Apex,</hi> then be ſure the Planet is direct, if in <hi>precedens, (as in</hi> ☿) then is he <hi>Retrograde,</hi> if iuſt one vppon another, then <hi>Stationary.</hi> And full eaſy will it be to imagin the ſpaces betweene the two <hi>Apices</hi> of each Planets carect, into ſeuen equall partes for the ſeuen dayes of the weeke included betweene them, as in the 2. Cap. you imagined the Squares into fiue partes, and ſo reddily to conceiue where each Planet is any of thoſe ſeuen dayes, which in none of them can exceede twiſe 7 Degrees, (the Moone ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted) whoſe gate in common accoumpt is euery two houres one whole Degree, and euery foure and twenty houres twelue Degrees. Wherefore for her, eyther you muſt relye vppon your Almanacke, or haue foure ſingle Carects at the leaſt to be ſet two dayes in ſunder apeece, that is to ſaye, the one to bee ſet at the Moones place
<pb facs="tcp:4837:11"/> for Sunday noone (for Aſtronomers alwayes begin their day at noone, becauſe the Meridian is <hi>Horizon rectus</hi>) the ſecond to be ſet for Tewſday noone, the third for Thurſday noone, and the fourth for Saterday noone, and ſo by adding or ſubducting of 12 degrees for a day, and two degrees for an houre, her place ſhall ſufficiently well be had. Her motion is very ſwift, and her <hi>Proſthaphereſis,</hi> or <hi>Aequacions,</hi> cauſed by her epicicles, may happily breede error of 7 or 8 degrees in one weeke, from that common accoumpt of two houres to a degree, otherwiſe two Carects might haue ſufficed, but in two dayes her greateſt gate being but 12 degrees either be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore or behinde one of the carects, can breede no error to be regarded, if you recken it from that carect vnto which ſhe is neereſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>Cap. 5. ¶ How by this new Aſtrolabe to finde the true place of the Sunne perpetually.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N my <hi>Organum Vranicum</hi> ſhortly like to come foorth, you ſhall haue the Kalender of the yere, the Cicle of the Sunne, and all ſuch neceſſary ſupplements. And therefore in this Aſtrolabe, which I do appoint to be alwayes anexed thereunto, and to be but the back ſide, or <hi>Dorſum Vranici,</hi> I haue framed no Kalender at all or Theoricke of the ☉ as commonly all other Aſtrolabes haue. Yet to ſerue the turne vntill the <hi>Vranicum</hi> come foorth, or for them that would content themſelues without the other, as happily ſome will in regard of the charge of the other, which can not well be framed but of mettall, I haue in the 12 Signes of the Zodiackes <hi>Orbs</hi> placed the 12 letters of the 12 Moneths, <hi>vz. I</hi> for Ianuary, <hi>F</hi> for February, &amp;c. at ſuch degree and minute of the-clipticke as they doe make their entraunce the <hi>Radicall</hi> yeare of my ſayd <hi>Vranicum,</hi> being the
<pb facs="tcp:4837:11"/> yeare after Chriſt 1600. by help of which you ſhall for euer it you will, finde the true place of the Sunne within 3 or 4 minutes, ſo you regard but three obſeruaunces which I ſhall heere deliuer you. The firſt is, concerning the Leape yeare, and is remedied by rebating ſome quarter of a degree for euery yeare following the Leape yeare till it be Leape yeare againe. The ſecond is, concerning the fiue odde dayes in the yeare aboue 360. and is remedied by rebating for euery day of the moneth, propoſed but one minute. The third is, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning ages paſt or to come, the remedie whereof, I will ſhew in the end of this Cap. Now therefore for the time pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, <hi>vz.</hi> for ſome 20 yeares if neede be before or behinde the yeare 1600. it ſerueth fitly as it is vpon euery Leape yeare, (becauſe his roote 1600 is a Leape yeare) without any obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uacion more then for the fiue odde dayes which is generall in euery yeare: and for any common yeare with very little trouble, as I ſhall ſhewe in this manner: Wherefore if you will know what degree and minute the Sunne is in vpon any day and yeare aſſigned. Firſt, ſeeke by the <hi>Zodiacke</hi> for the letter of the Moneth in which your day is (<hi>vz. For the let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter I ſeruing for Iune, which is placed at the</hi> 20 <hi>degree and ſomewhat more in</hi> ♊, <hi>and the number</hi> 6 <hi>aſcribed thereto, ſignifieth</hi> 6 <hi>minutes more then the</hi> 20 <hi>degrees, the exact place of that letter I.</hi>) And from that letter <hi>(vz. I)</hi> number for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards ſo many degrees of the Clipticke as your day (<hi>the</hi> 8 <hi>of Iune</hi>) propoſed is within your moneth <hi>(Iune)</hi> propoſed, rebating ſo many minutes, according to the ſecond obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaunce before mentioned (<hi>vz. for your</hi> 8 <hi>dayes, recken</hi> 8 <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees in ſequens of that</hi> 20 <hi>deg.</hi> 6 <hi>min. of</hi> ♊ <hi>lacking</hi> 8 <hi>min.</hi>) and where that accoumpt falleth out (<hi>which you ſhall finde vppon that reckning and rebating of</hi> 8 <hi>minutes, to be</hi> 27 <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees</hi> 58 <hi>minutes of</hi> ♊.) there ſhall be the true place of the ☉ if it be a Leape yeare (<hi>as this yeare</hi> 1596 <hi>is</hi>) and there (<hi>vz. at the ſaide</hi> 27 <hi>degrees</hi> 58 <hi>minutes of</hi> ♊) you may place the Carect of the Sunne for that day, as in the laſt Chapter is
<pb facs="tcp:4837:12"/> taught. But if it ſhall be the firſt yeare after the Leape yeare, then ſhall you rebate a quarter of a degree, or 14 ⅓ min. (if you will be preciſe) if the ſecond yeare, then rebate halfe a degree, if the third, rebate ¾ of a degree, and then euery Leape yeare it returneth to his owne place againe. And this for almoſt twenty yeares eyther before or behinde the <hi>Radi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call</hi> yeare 1600 ſhall ſerue paſſing well and reddye within ſome foure or fiue minutes, but for any time after the yeare 1600 you ſhall neede but adde, and for any time before ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract ſome halfe quarter of a Degree (or 8 ¾ minutes if you will be preciſe) for euery 20 yeares. (<hi>As for Example for the place of the</hi> ☉ <hi>the</hi> 8 <hi>day of March in the yeare</hi> 1700. <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe betweene the yeare</hi> 1600 <hi>and</hi> 1700, <hi>there are fiue times</hi> 20 <hi>yeares, therefore I adde fiue diquarters of a degree (or to be preciſe fiue times</hi> 8 ¾ <hi>minutes which maketh</hi> 44 ¾ <hi>minutes) vnto the foreſaid</hi> 27 <hi>degr.</hi> 58 <hi>min. in</hi> ♊, <hi>and it maketh</hi> 28 <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees,</hi> 42 ¾ <hi>minutes, which is the true place of the</hi> ☉ <hi>on the</hi> 8 <hi>day of Iune, Anno.</hi> 1700.) And becauſe you ſhall worke the more certaine, I haue to euery of the 12 letters of the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neths, ſet the number of the minutes of that degree where his right place ſhould be, which place is alſo deſcryed by a little ſtroke or ſtring cutting the true place of the ſame Degree, and leading thence to the letter, if it be not placed directly therewith.</p>
               <p>Alſo you muſt not forget for ages paſt or to come, to adde or ſubtract the <hi>Aequacion</hi> of the 8 Speere, as in the 30 Cap. ſhall be ſhewed according to the words <hi>Adiectiue</hi> or <hi>Abla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue</hi> there mentioned, for that will from time to time alter this true place of the Sunne, euen vnto 1 ⅙ Degrees, about 800 yeares to come, or paſſed. Although ſome others haue ouerſlipped in their Theoricks of the ☉ both this, and the third obſeruacion before. (<hi>For example you ſhall by the</hi> 30 <hi>Cap. finde the</hi> 8 <hi>Speares Aequation</hi> 12 ¼ <hi>minutes ablatiue for the yeare</hi> 1700, <hi>and ſo will the true place then be but</hi> 28 <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees</hi> 30 ½ <hi>minutes for the</hi> 8 <hi>of Iune.</hi>)</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:4837:12"/>
               <p>After many words thus ſpent, the precept is briefely thus: Suppoſe euery degree of the-clipticke to be a day of the yeare, rebating for euery day a minute, and for euery of the three common yeares 14 ⅓ minutes, and thus farre it ſerueth for all times. But now i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> your time be after 1600, you muſt for the <hi>motus equalis compoſitus</hi> adde 8 ¾ degrees for euery 20 yeares, and for euery 20 yeare before 1650 adde 5 min. for the 8 ſpheeres equation: and contrariwiſe, if being before 1600 and after 1650 you muſt ſubduct as much. Note, that I haue been ſithence enformed that our honourable Lords de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted the 3 of Iune, but let the 8 of Iune now ſtand for the example, nothing hurtfull.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>Cap. 6. ¶ How to rectifye the true place of the Sunne to all places of the world.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Y good meaning determining this <hi>Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>labe</hi> as a fit recreacion or play-game for trauellers by Sea, to driue away the tedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes of their iourneying, may ſooneſt of all deceiue them in getting the true place of the ☉, whether by the <hi>Ephemeris,</hi> or by the laſt Cap. or by my <hi>Organum Vranicum,</hi> if they haue not a ſpeciall regard to the changing of their <hi>Meridians</hi> as they trauayle: for which cauſe, I haue cauſed a new deſcription of the tereſtriall Globe to be made after my faſhion in one face, where others make them ſtill in two faces: and both that tereſtriall and this celeſtiall, are principally meant by me to ſerue vnto my <hi>Vranicum,</hi> and to be placed in the inner ſides of his caſe as neceſſary appendices, though of it<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe it bee an Inſtrument ſufficient without theſe. Of this tereſtriall I doe at this time (although hauing ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye extraordinary conceites to applye him for Nauigati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and other neceſſities to write of) determine to deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer but this Chapter, therein to let you vnderſtande,
<pb facs="tcp:4837:13"/> that in the limbe circle about it which repreſenteth the <hi>Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quinoctiall</hi> circle at the Meridian cutting vpon <hi>London,</hi> I haue placed a rundle with a croſſe, and at the oppoſite Meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dian the number of 12. ſignifying 12 houres, and betweene theſe on both ſides are 11 other rundles for houres, ſo is that whole circle deuided into twiſe 12 houres, and numbred both wayes from the croſſe rundle, ſignifying how many houres the Sunne or any Planet or Starre hath to go from our Meridian at <hi>London</hi> (when any of them come vnto it) before it can come to the Meridian of another place, or being in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother place, how many houres it muſt go ere it come to ours. And in regard that the gate of the ☉ is euery 24 houres a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of the-clipticke, therefore you muſt adde or ſubtract from his place found either in the laſt Cap. or the <hi>Ephemeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des,</hi> or my <hi>Vranicum,</hi> according to the rate thereof, <hi>vz.</hi> for euery 12 houres, about 30 minutes of a degree, and for 6 houres 15 minutes, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>As for example, admit you being a trauayler ſhould be the fift day of March 1598 in the 4. Cap. mentioned in the great City of <hi>Quinſay</hi> in the countrey of <hi>China,</hi> and there ſeeking for the true place of the Sunne at noone, had found it 25 de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees 3 minutes in ♓ as in the 4. Cap. it was. Now becauſe the Meridian of <hi>Quinſay</hi> appeareth in this Tereſtriall by the ſaid houre rundles almoſt 9 houres diſtant from the Meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dian of <hi>London</hi> or rather of <hi>Anwerp</hi> if you worke by <hi>Stadius Ephemerides,</hi> or the laſt Cap. and that towards the Eaſt: Therefore the ☉ commeth ſo much ſooner to the meridian or noone at <hi>Quinſay,</hi> for which cauſe you muſt in this caſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate ſo much of the Sunnes diurnall gate of 60 minutes, as 9 houres commeth to, <hi>vz.</hi> 22 minutes, ſo will the Sunne that day at noone in that countrye be but 24 degrees 41 min. in ♓, which in the 4 Cap. was found to be 25 degrees 3 minutes in ♓. And if your place had beene ſo much Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, then ſhould you haue added 22 minutes vnto 25 de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees 3 minutes in ♓. You may alſo performe the ſame
<pb facs="tcp:4837:13"/> reddily by the next Cap. applying the Labell vnto 30 minut. of the ſextans, for ſo much is the ſemidiurnall gate of the Sunne commonly.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>Cap. 7. ¶ How to rectifye the place of the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> or of any other Planet to any other Meridian.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here is more neede to haue regard of this matter for the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g>, becauſe her motion is very ſwift euen euery two houres about a degree, then in any other of the Planets: and for reddyer performance heereof, the <hi>Horarium Planetarium</hi> in the 29 Cap. mentioned, ſhall yeeld you ſpeciall helpe, if you imagine the 10 houres of the Arch of the ſextans to be 10 degrees, and cauſe the planetary Index to be numbred for this purpoſe into 12 houres from the Centre outwards.</p>
               <p>Now when you will rectifie the true place of any Planet (<hi>admit of the</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g>) at noone any day propoſed (<hi>admit the</hi> 5. <hi>day of March</hi> 1598) to another Meridian <hi>(admit to the Meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dian of Quinſay.)</hi> Firſt you ſhall get the ſemidiurnall gate of the Planet by taking the motion of the day propoſed (<hi>vz.</hi> 2 <hi>degr.</hi> 40 <hi>min. in</hi> ♋) out of the motion of the day following (<hi>being the</hi> 6 <hi>day of March, and the Moones place or motion then</hi> 15 <hi>degr.</hi> 1. <hi>min. in</hi> ♋) and take halfe the remaine (<hi>vz.</hi> 6 <hi>degr.</hi> 10 <hi>min.</hi>) which you ſhall ſeeke in the arche of the ſextans (<hi>as though they were</hi> 6 <hi>houres</hi> 10 <hi>min.</hi>) and thereto ſet the Index, there let him ſtay. Then as in the laſt Cap. is taught, ſeeke the houre diſtaunce of the Meridian of the other place <hi>(vz. of Quinſay)</hi> from yours, <hi>vz.</hi> from that of <hi>Anwerpe</hi> (for <hi>Stadius</hi>) but for my <hi>Vranicum</hi> from <hi>London, (admit the houre diſtaunce</hi> 8 <hi>houres and an halfe</hi>) and that diſtaunce ſeeke in the Index planted as before by the numbers reckned from the Centre outwards vnto 12, and marke what paralell
<pb facs="tcp:4837:14"/> cutteth the Index there (<hi>vz. at the ſayd</hi> 8 ½ <hi>houre thereof</hi>) and follow it to the arche of the <hi>Sextans,</hi> which ſhall there ſhew you (4 <hi>degrees</hi> 30 <hi>minutes</hi>) the motion of the Planet anſwerable to that houre diſtaunce of their Meridians, which if it be Weſtwards from your Meridian, you ſhall adde to, if Eaſtwards <hi>(as heere it is)</hi> then ſubtract out of the place of the Planet found (<hi>vz. out of</hi> 2 <hi>degrees</hi> 40 <hi>minutes of</hi> ♋) and ſo ſhall you haue (28 <hi>degrees</hi> 10 <hi>minutes in</hi> ♊) the true recti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied place of the Planet to that Meridian propoſed.</p>
               <p>Note, that for ♄, ♃, ♂, ♀, ☿, and the ☉, whoſe ſemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>durnall gates ſeldome exceede minutes, you may take 3 or 4 houres of the <hi>Sextans</hi> for one degree, and worke as before moſt exact.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>Cap. 8. ¶ How to know the declinacion and right aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion of any Planet, fixed Starre, or point of the heauens, and their degree of Culminacion.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here are in the <hi>Mater,</hi> or <hi>Celeſtiall</hi> of this <hi>Aſtrolabe,</hi> to auoide confuſion, only two ſorts of circles delineated, &amp; thoſe are the circles of the-clipticks longitude and latitude in the 2. Cap. mentioned, iſſuing from his Pole <hi>D</hi> to his oppoſite. And the very like vnto thoſe ought to haue been delineated, iſſuing from the Poles of the world, limitting the right aſſentions and declinations of the Starres, in regard of the Equinoctiall, and are commonly called Meridians and Paralells, which becauſe the nature of this proiectement doth caſt the Meridians into ſtreight lines iſſuing from the Poles, both lodged in the Centre vnto euery of the 360 degrees of the Equinoctiall, or rather of the limbe and the parallells into concentricke circles, they are therefore ſupplyed by playing about the radiall degrees
<pb facs="tcp:4837:14"/> of the noone-lines on the Centre, by the degrees of the limbe, and might as well be done by a thred &amp; pearle applyed to the radyall degrees of the Scale planted at the beginning of ♋.</p>
               <p>Further you ſhall vnderſtand that countrey is ſayd to haue a right <hi>Horizon,</hi> vnto which ſome one of the Meridians is <hi>Horizon,</hi> that is to ſay, where the <hi>Aequinoctiall</hi> paſſeth by the <hi>Zenith</hi> or point directly ouer head, called the <hi>Verticall point,</hi> and both the poles of the world euen with the <hi>Horizon,</hi> and neither of them eleuated, all other <hi>Horizons</hi> where either Pole is eleuated, are called oblique <hi>Horizons.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now therefore when you are to get the right aſcenſion of any Planet-Starre, or point of the heauens aſſigned, you are but to learne what Meridian and Paralell cutteth the ſame, and if you do but lay the noone-line thereon, it ſheweth you in the limbe the right aſcention, and in the ſcale of the Radiall degrees on the noone-line the declinacion. For ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, the Sunnes <hi>Apex</hi> placed at the 26 degree 3 minut. of ♓ by the 2 cap. lay the noone-line thereto, and it ſhall ſhewe you in the limbe 356 degrees 25 minutes his right aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cencion, and among the radiall degrees of the noone-line 1 degr. 30 min. his declinacion, and that Southwards of the Equinoctiall. For the 5 day of March 1598 likewiſe apply the noone-line vnto the chiefe Carect of ♄ there placed at 2 degr. 27 min. in ♎, and in latitude 2 degr 44 min. North, and it ſhall ſhew you in the limbe 182 degrees his right aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cencion, and among the radiall degrees, 1 degr. 10 min. his declinacion South from the equinoctiall the ſame 5 of March 1598. Againe, if for any Starre, as admit the great Starre of the firſt light in or neere the eye of the Bull, called <hi>Ocu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus tauri,</hi> the noone-line layd thereon, ſheweth in the limbe 63 degrees 30 min. his right aſcencion, and 16 degrees his declinacion North from the equinoctiall, though he be in lati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude South from the-clipticke, and it cutteth in the <hi>Zodiacke</hi> the 5 degree 35 min. of ♊ his degree of culminacion: for al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> degree of the-clipticke which coaſcendeth or cutteth
<pb facs="tcp:4837:15"/> any Meridian or right <hi>Horizon</hi> with any Starre, or other point of the heauens, is called the degree of his <hi>Culminacion,</hi> becauſe the Meridian of any place is called <hi>Culmen Celi.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>Cap. 9. ¶ How to finde the true Meridian in any countrey by helpe of this Aſtrolabe.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Meridian circle of any latitude, is that great circle of the Spheare which paſſeth by the <hi>Zenith</hi> or verticall point of that place, and a line drawne by his two interſections with the <hi>Horizon</hi> there, is called the Meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dian line. Alſo, that Starre which in this Aſtrolabe you ſee in the outermoſt tip of the tayle of <hi>Vrſa Minor,</hi> is commonly called the Pole ſtarre, in Latin <hi>Stella polaris,</hi> or <hi>Cinoſura,</hi> which in this age is ſome 3 ½ degree di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant from the true North point or pole of the world, although the ordinary ſort take it to be the Pole it ſelfe, yet in euery age to come by reaſon of the foreſaid ſliding backe of the equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noctiall points, he ſhall draw neerer and neerer to the Pole vntill the yeare 2220 after Chriſt, and then ſhall he be but 30 minutes from the Pole, and his longitude ſhall be then 0 in ♋, from whence he will then begin to elongate againe from the Pole till he come to 0 in ♑ about the yeare 15120, at which time his diſtance from the Pole ſhall be 47 degrees 30 minutes. And whereas <hi>Petrus Nonius</hi> ſayth, that in times paſt he hath been 12 degrees 24 minutes from the Pole, and is now 3 degrees 30 minutes, happily he meaneth from the creation of the world.</p>
               <p>This Pole-Starre in our age is found to culminate with the 6 degr. 20 min. of ♈, and to be 88 degr. 24 min. declining North from the equinoctiall: on which 6 degr. 20 min. of ♈ if you lay the Noone-line, you ſhall firſt thereby ſee what
<pb facs="tcp:4837:15"/> Starres do continually culminate or come vnto the Meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dian with it, and you ſhall finde it to cut on the faire Starre of the third light, in the pummell of the chayer of <hi>Caſſiopeia,</hi> and another of the ſame light the northermoſt of the girdle of <hi>Andromeda,</hi> and in the oppoſite part, <hi>vz.</hi> by the North line, you ſhall ſee the 60 degr. 20 min of ♎ to culminate almoſt with the innermoſt of the three in the tayle tayle of <hi>Vrſa ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ior</hi> called <hi>Alioth,</hi> and two of the Starres of ♍, But that of <hi>Caſſiopeia,</hi> and that of <hi>Vrſa maior</hi> are beſt for this purpoſe. Hauing thus by your Aſtrolabe found out a Starre or two which haue the ſame degree of culminating any Meridian as the Pole-Starre hath, now ſhall you neede but in any ſtarry night to hang vp ſome line, or erect ſome round pole or ſtaffe perpendiculer to your <hi>Horizon,</hi> and then watch the going about of the Starres, vntill ſome one of thoſe two Starres come with the ſayd Pole-Starre very euen and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly with your perpendiculer, for then be ſure that thoſe two are both directly in the Meridian: Wherefore you ſhall then ſpeedily plant another perpendiculer iuſt betweene your firſt and the ſayd two Starres, and there let them remaine continually, for they ſhall ſerue you for many good purpoſes at any time after both day and night, in ſtead of a Meridian, I could ſet you downe many wayes more, but this is moſt pertinent to this Inſtrument, and is of all other the readyeſt, eſpecially whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as by the 22 Cap. following you ſhall before<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand know what houre theſe Starres will come to the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ridian, that you neede not watch long for them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <head>Cap. 10. ¶ How to attaine the latitude or Poles eleuation in any Countrey vnknowne, and to chooſe out the Verti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call point in the noone-line, the Horizontall point in the North line, with the Zenith line ſeruing thereunto.</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:4837:16"/>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Latitude of any place, is the diſtaunce of his Verticall point from the <hi>Aequinoctiall,</hi> counted by the degrees of his Meridian circle on the South part, and is alwayes equall to the eleuacion of the Pole of the world aboue the <hi>Horizon</hi> counted in the ſame <hi>Meridian</hi> on the North part, either of which can neuer exceede 90 degrees: for which cauſe, there are in the <hi>Zenitfer</hi> 90 Zenith lines deſcribed, to ſerue euery turne. And the reddieſt and moſt ſure way to get the latitude in any ſtrange place, hauing by the laſt Cap. ſetled your Meridian, is to take the Meridian altitudes of ſome one North Starre that neuer commeth South of the Zenith there, both aboue and vnder the Pole, then take the greater Altitude out of the leſſer, and of the remaine adde the one halfe to the leſſer, ſo haue you the latitude or Poles Eleuauion ſought, whoſe complement is the Equinoctials eleuacion aboue the South point of the <hi>Horizon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For example, admit the firſt Starre of the tayle of <hi>Vrſa maior</hi> called <hi>Alioth,</hi> if you obſerue his comming to the <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ridian</hi> aboue the Pole-Starre, and there finde his altitude to be 84 degrees high, and afterwards finding him againe in the <hi>Meridian</hi> vnder the Pole (which will be ſome 12 houres betweene) and there but 19 ⅓ degrees high, then take 19 ⅓ out of 84 there reſteth 64 ⅔, halfe that being 32 ⅓ added to 19 ⅓ maketh 51 ⅔ our eleuacion heere at <hi>Reading,</hi> and ſo much is our Zenith, or Verticall point, all is one, diſtant from the Equinoctiall, and that 51 ⅔ taken out of 90, leaueth the complement 38 ⅓ the Equinoctials height aboue the Horizon in our Meridian.</p>
               <p>Now, if you will chooſe out in the noone-line of the Zenit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer the <hi>Verticall point</hi> fitting thereunto, recken thereon from the Equinoctialls interſection, with the noone-line by the
<pb facs="tcp:4837:16"/> radiall degrees and numbers thereon ſet betweene the Centre and <hi>Meridies,</hi> your latitude found, for there ſhall be your <hi>Verticall point</hi> deſired (<hi>vz. for our Eleuacion heere at Reading, the Pole being</hi> 51 ⅔ <hi>degrees high, I reckon that by the numbers in the noone-line, and there I conclude is our Verticall point, or of any Countrey hauing like la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude.</hi>) Likewiſe reckon on the North line from the Centre towardes <hi>Media nox,</hi> your ſayde latitude founde (<hi>vz. the ſaid</hi> 51 <hi>degrees</hi> 40 <hi>minutes,</hi>) and there ſhall be the place or point of your Horizons interſection, with the North part of your Meridian (51 <hi>degrees</hi> 40 <hi>minutes vnder the Pole</hi>) which I call the Horizontall point. And betweene the Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall and Horizontall points thus founde, you ſhall alwaies finde 90 Radiall degrees complete and no more, which 90 degrees are the true interſections or croſſings of the 90 <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>micantares</hi> of that latitude with the North part of the Meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dian, which for breuities ſake I will heereafter call the North degrees, and thoſe 90 degrees of the noone-line from the Verticall point towards <hi>Meridies,</hi> I will call the South degrees, both which in a particular would be numbred from the two Horizontall points, vnto the Zenith or Verticall point, there ending at 90 accordingly.</p>
               <p>Now for the Zenith line in the Zenitfer appertaining to your latitude found, it is eaſily choſen by the numbers aſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed to the inner ends of thoſe 90 Zenith lines, as in the 1 cap. is ſhewed, which 90 inner ends are y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 90 Zenith points, and do anſwere by the fiduciall line of the Curſor, vnto the 90 Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall points of the noone-line, (<hi>vz. the</hi> 51 ⅔ <hi>Zenith line muſt be choſen for our latitude heere at Reading,</hi>) euery of them carrying his 90 <hi>Almicantare</hi> rootes diſtinguiſhed by the cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued lines, and numbred from their outermoſt end inwards to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards their Zenith points, as in the 1. Cap. is ſhewed.</p>
               <p>Your Verticall point, Horizon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>, and your Zenith line appertaining thus found, you muſt in any wiſe marke them ſpecially from the reſt except your memory be good, the reddier to finde them in all your actions.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:4837:17"/>
               <head>Cap. 11. ¶ How to take the Meridian Altitude of the Sunne, or any Planet or Starre, and thereby to get the latitude in any Countrey.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is a matter very eaſy and common, either by a Quadrant with a line and plummet, or by the circle or this Aſtrolabe hanged per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendiculer, furniſhed with a rule and two ſightes to take an altitude: for the Sunne, by ſuffering the Sunne-beames to pearce the ſight-holes, and for Starres by applying the ſightes to your eye, which altitude of the Sunne or any Starre being taken in the direct South or North by help of your Meridian ſet by the 9 cap. is called the Meridian altitude. But if you haue no Meridian ſet, place your Quadrant or Aſtrolabe to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the South or North, and thereby obſerue the ſeuerall altitudes of the Sunne or Starres as they riſe higher and higher, and the higheſt ſhall be the Meridian altitude. Where note, that ſuch Starres whoſe declinacions exceede the lati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes complement, do come twiſe vnto the Meridian at 12 houres betweene, yet neuer come South of the Zenith, or Verticall point.</p>
               <p>The Meridian altitude thus had (<hi>As for example heere at Reading the</hi> 2 <hi>of October</hi> 1596 <hi>about</hi> 3 <hi>of the clocke in the morning, I obſerued the comming of the Starre oculus Tauri to the Meridian, and there tooke his Meridian Altitude by a Quadrant</hi> 54 ⅓ <hi>degrees</hi>) take it out of 90 degrees (<hi>vz.</hi> 54 ⅓ <hi>out of</hi> 90) ſo haue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> (35 ⅔) the complement or verticall diſtance of the Planet or Starre (<hi>oculus</hi> ♉) propoſed, from the Zenith of your being. Now if this Meridian Altitude happen on the North from your Zenith, then muſt you place
<pb facs="tcp:4837:17"/> the North line of your Zenitfer on the centre of your Planet or Starre found out in this Aſtrolabe: but if it happen South of your Zenith, (<hi>As heere this Meridian altitude of ocul.</hi> ♉ <hi>did from our Zenith at Reading</hi>) then bring the noone-line there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to. And from that touching of the Starres centre therewith, (<hi>which you ſhall finde to touch at</hi> 16 <hi>degrees, as they are on the noone-line there numbered</hi>) you ſhall recken inwards towards the centre of the Celeſtiall ſo many degrees as the ſayd verticall diſtaunce amounteth vnto, (<hi>vz. the ſaide</hi> 35 ⅔ <hi>degrees</hi>) and the end of that reckoning ſhall aſſuredly ſhewe you (51 ⅔) in the noone-line the Zenith point of your being, whoſe number aſcribed (<hi>vz. the ſaide</hi> 51 ⅔) is your latitude deſired, (<hi>thereby I might conclude, that the latitude heere at Reading was</hi> 51 ⅔ <hi>degrees</hi>) whoſe Horizontall point and Zenith line you may eaſily finde out by the laſt Cap.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <head>Cap. 12. ¶ How to know what day of the yeare it were if it were forgotten.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Et the Latitude by the 10 or 11 cap. (<hi>admit our latitude</hi> 51 ⅔ <hi>degrees</hi>) and the meridian altitude of the ☉ by the laſt cap. (<hi>admit</hi> 25 <hi>degrees</hi>) recken the complement thereof (<hi>vz.</hi> 65 <hi>degrees</hi>) in the noone-line from the <hi>Verticall point</hi> towards <hi>Meridies,</hi> and looke what radiall degrees it falleth at (<hi>you ſhall finde it at</hi> 13 ½ <hi>degrees Southwards from the Equinoctialls interſection</hi>) and apply that degree by moouing about the <hi>Zenitfer</hi> vnto the clipticke circle, according as you geſſe the time of the yeare to be, <hi>vz.</hi> If you thinke it to be betweene Midſomer and Chriſtmas, then apply the ſame 13 ⅓ <hi>degr.</hi>) vnto the autum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall hemicicle, where ♋ ☊ ♍ ♎ ♏ &amp; ♐ are, (<hi>where it muſt needes touch vpon the</hi> 24 <hi>degree of</hi> ♒) if betweene Chriſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas
<pb facs="tcp:4837:18"/> and Midſomer then vnto the vernall hemicircle of the others Signes (<hi>where it muſt needes our the</hi> 6 of ♏) and there ſhall moſt aſſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>edly be th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> tru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> the Sunne for that day. Which bring had: then you may eaſily by the 5. Cap. euerſed as well finde the day anſwerable thereto, as there you found the Sunnes place anſwerable to the day <hi>vice verſa.</hi> Prouided that the Sunnes place be rectified as in the 6. Cap. if neede be.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <head>Cap. 13. ¶ How to know what it is a clocke at any time either night or day, by the S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nne, Planets, or Starres.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>Ou muſt alwayes intend that the Planets are weekely placed, as in the 3. Cap. is taught. Alſo obſerue this rule generall, to keepe the noone-line of the <hi>Zenitfer</hi> ſtill vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, by turning about your <hi>Aſtrolabe,</hi> imagining your face turned ſtill to the South, except when you are ſpecially to deale with the North line, then keepe him vpwards, and then imagine your face turned towards the North. Now when you de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to knowe the houre of the day or night, you ſhall as in the laſt Cap. is mentioned, either by a Quadrant, or this Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>labe, take the Altitude of the Sunne at any time in the day or in the night of any Starre. (<hi>For Example this yeare</hi> 1596 <hi>the</hi> 2 <hi>of October in the morning at my poore houſe at Swal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowfeyld by Reading, to ſee how the time paſſed, I tooke the altitude of the Sunne</hi> 15 <hi>degrees high, And the ſame euening I tooke the altitude of the great Starre Arcturus</hi> 10 <hi>degrees high towards the Weſt</hi>) Which had, then ſhall you prepare your <hi>Almicantifer</hi> vnto that altitude, thus: In the Zenith line choſen by the 7. Cap. for your place <hi>(vz. in the</hi> 51 ⅔ <hi>Zenith line for vs heere about Reading)</hi> ſeeke out a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong his Almicantare rootes the number of that Altitude
<pb facs="tcp:4837:18"/> taken, (<hi>vz. in the morning I ſought</hi> 15 <hi>for the</hi> ☉, <hi>and at night</hi> 10 <hi>for Arcturus</hi>) &amp; there plant the Curſor, then reckon on the North line fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> your <hi>Horizontall</hi> point found by the 7 inwards towards the centre the ſame altitude againe (<hi>vz. fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Hori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zontall point of our latitude, being the</hi> 51 ⅔ <hi>deg. of the North<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>line counted from the center, I reckoned inwards for the</hi> ☉ 15 <hi>degrees, and for Arcturus</hi> 10 <hi>degrees, the one fell out at</hi> 36 ⅔ <hi>degrees from the center, the other at</hi> 41 ⅔) and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, ſet the pointer of the <hi>Almicantifer,</hi> which poynter and Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor ſo ſet, I call the <hi>Almicantifer</hi> prepared: Then leade about the <hi>Almicantifer,</hi> which muſt alſo leade after him the noone-line, vntill the pointer come to touch exactly either the <hi>Apex</hi> of the Sunnes Carect, or the very centre of the Starre by which ſoeuer you deale, and this I call the applying of the pointer to any Planet or Starre: There hold the Zenitfer faſt, and ſlide downe the Curſor to the centre, applying there his Fiduciall line labell-wiſe to the Sunne, which ſhall ſhew you in the houre circle the houre deſired, and this I call labelling of the Sunne to the houre circle: Yet vpon theſe condicions, that if you deale for the Eaſt Hemiſpheare, that is to ſay, if your altitude taken were on the Eaſt part of the Meridian, <hi>vz.</hi> betweene the North and South Eaſtwards (<hi>as for the</hi> ☉ <hi>it was</hi>) then in this leading about ſhall the <hi>Almi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cantifer</hi> play leftwards of the noone-line towards 6 of clocke in the morning of the houre circle which I call the Eaſt He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſpheare, and ſo to leade the noone-line after it leftwards, but if your altitude taken were on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Weſt part <hi>(as for Arctu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus it was)</hi> then ſhall the <hi>Almicantifer</hi> play and keepe on the right ſide of the noone-line towards 6 of clocke at night, and leade him about rightwards after him (<hi>According to which precept, the ſaid</hi> 2 <hi>of October in the morning, I applied the Almicantifer his pointer prepared as is ſaid vnto</hi> 15 <hi>deg. to the Apex of the</hi> ☉ (<hi>placed as is ſaid at</hi> 20 ⅓ <hi>of</hi> ♎) <hi>in the Eaſt He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſpheere, and there did I labell to the Sunne, which ſhewed me halfe an houre paſt</hi> 8 <hi>in the morning, the houre deſired.
<pb facs="tcp:4837:19"/> Likewiſe at night I applied the pointer prepared, and planted for</hi> 10 <hi>degrees vnto Arcturus in the Weſt Hemiſpheare, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe Arcturus was in the Weſt, and then againe I labelled to the</hi> ☉ <hi>which ſhewed me in the Houre circle halfe an houre paſt</hi> 7 <hi>of the clocke at night, the houre deſired:</hi> For alwayes <hi>(Locus Solis oſtendit horam.)</hi> And I dare boldly ſay, that ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer was ſeene before this more facillitie to know the houre by the Starres, by any other Aſtrolabe, or Inſtrument whatſoeuer.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="chapter">
               <head>Cap. 14. ¶ Another more eaſy way to finde the houre by the Starres.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Auing your Meridian planted about your dwelling place, as in the 6 Cap. is taught, ſee into the element if any Starre you know well (as by the 25 Cap. you ſhall eaſily know hem all) be euen therewith either on the South or North part. And vpon that Starre ſought in the Celeſtiall, place accordingly the North line or noone line (either of them now eſteemed from the Zenith point) and there labell to the ☉, ſo ſhall the houre ſought ſhew it ſelfe in the houre circle vnder the fiduciall line of the Labell or Almicantifer now vſed Labell-wiſe after the woonted manner, this needeth no example.</p>
               <p>If you haue no Meridian perpendiculers ſet, you may at any time preſently ſet them with two ſtickes by the Pole-Starre it ſelfe ſufficient for this purpoſe. I my ſelfe alwayes kept a ſtanding marke ready ſet in ſuch ſort, that ſome tree, chimney top, or gable end, ſhould be directly South from the ſame. If no Starre be in the South or North, it is not hard to geſſe the diſtaunce of the neereſt you ſee, and place your noone or North line accordingly, eſpecially by two Starres, on either ſide one, to marke what part of their diſtance your
<pb facs="tcp:4837:19"/> Meridian cutteth, and accordingly to place the noone or North line betweene them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="chapter">
               <head>Cap. 15. ¶ Another eaſy way by the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g>.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Ake the houre which the ſhade of the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> giueth on any Sunne-dyall, ſeeke the ſame houre in the houre circle, and labell it to the Moones Carect planted by the 3. Cap. and then holding faſt the <hi>Zenitfer,</hi> labell to the Sunnes Carect, which ſhall ſhew in the houre circle the houre deſired.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="chapter">
               <head>Cap. 16. ¶ How to know the meridian Altitude of the Sunne, or any other Planet, Starre, or point of the heauens in any countrey, and what houre of the day or night any of them ſhall culminate, or come to the Meridian of that place.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Carects being planted by the 3 Cap. you ſhall but applye the noone-line to the Apex or Centre of the Planet, Starre, or point deſired, and the degrees there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on found betweene the Verticall point and it taken out of 90, leaueth the Meridian al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude deſired, whether it be North or South, and there alſo if you labell to the Sunne, it ſhall ſhew you in the houre circle the time when that Planet, Starre, or point, commeth to the Meridian. (<hi>For example, the noone-line brought to the Sunnes chiefe Apex, being planted by the</hi> 3 <hi>cap. at</hi> 263 <hi>min. in</hi> ♓, <hi>his place for the</hi> 5 <hi>of March</hi> 1598. <hi>you ſhall finde him
<pb facs="tcp:4837:20"/> by the degrees of the noone-line</hi> 53 <hi>degrees diſtaunt from our Verticall point heere at Reading therein, vz. from the</hi> 51 ⅔ <hi>degr. thereof, which</hi> 53 <hi>taken out of</hi> 90, <hi>leaueth</hi> 37 <hi>the Meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dian altitude.</hi> In like manner for any Starre, <hi>Admit oculus tauri the noone-line applyed to his middle pricke, you ſhall finde it diſtaunt from our Verticall point</hi> 35 ⅔ <hi>degr. that taken out of</hi> 90, <hi>leaueth</hi> 54 ⅓ <hi>his Meridian altitude,</hi> As if you make tryall by obſeruacion, as in the 8 Cap. is taught, you ſhall finde it ſo. <hi>And if you there labell to the</hi> ☉, <hi>you ſhall finde it to cut in the houre-circle</hi> 4 <hi>of clocke in the after noone, and almoſt halfe an houre paſt, which is the time that oculus tauri ſhall come vnto the Meridian the ſayd</hi> 6 <hi>of March</hi> 1598. But when you worke for the Sunne as before, he onely is himſelfe the pointer of houres, and therefore muſt needes be in the Meridian at Noone, or 12 of clocke. But if it be for any North Starre that neuer ſetteth, and that you would know his meridian altitude vnder the Pole, apply the North line thereto, and the degrees thereof betweene it and the <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rizontall</hi> point is your deſire, and there alſo labell to the Sunne, and it ſhall ſhew you the houre.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="chapter">
               <head>Cap. 17. ¶ How to know the houre of Sunne-riſing and ſetting, and the length of the day and night, together with his oblique aſcencion, and his dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference of aſcencion any day in the yeare.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>Our day and yeare propoſed (<hi>Admit the ſaid</hi> 8 <hi>day of Iune this yeare</hi> 1596 <hi>in the</hi> 3 <hi>Cap. mentioned, when our moſt noble Lords lanched from Plimmouth towardes Spayne</hi>) and the Sunnes <hi>Apex</hi> placed by the 3 cap. (<hi>vnto</hi> 27 <hi>degrees</hi> 58 <hi>min. of</hi> ♊) Then ſhall you ſet the Curſor vnto the outer end of the Zenith
<pb facs="tcp:4837:20"/> line of your countrey, (<hi>vz. vnto the</hi> 0 <hi>almicantare roote of the</hi> 51 <hi>Zenith line being for the latitude of Plymouth,</hi>) and there faſtening the Curſor apply the pointer vnto the <hi>Hori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zontall</hi> point (<hi>of Plimouth, being the</hi> 51 <hi>degree of the North line</hi>) and this I call preparing of the Zenitfer to the Horizon. Now, firſt to begin for the Sunne-riſing, being thus prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, you ſhall according to the precept in the 9 Cap. let the <hi>Almicantifer</hi> play on the Eaſt Hemicicle, and there apply his pointer to the Sunnes Apex (<hi>at</hi> 27 <hi>degr.</hi> 58 <hi>min. in</hi> ♊) there hold faſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Zenitfer and Labell to the Sunne, ſo ſhall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oure circle (4 <hi>of clock in the morning, and ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what leſſe</hi>) the time of the Sunne-riſing for your (8 <hi>of Iune</hi> 1596 <hi>at Plimouth</hi>) day and yeare propoſed. And if there alſo you labell to the Eaſt point or 6 of clock in the morning of the houre circle, it ſhall ſhew you in the limbe of the Celeſtiall (56 <hi>degr.</hi> 20 <hi>min.</hi>) the oblique aſcencion of the Sunne for that time and place he is in, which taken out of the right aſcencion of his place (<hi>of</hi> 27 <hi>degr.</hi> 58 <hi>min. of</hi> ♊, <hi>being</hi> 87 ½ <hi>degr.</hi>) had by the 8 Cap. there ſhall remaine (31 <hi>deg.</hi> 10 <hi>min.</hi>) the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of aſcencion. In the very like manner worke for the Sunne-ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ting, by letting the <hi>Almicantifer</hi> to play on the Weſt Hemicicle, and there apply the pointer againe to the Sunnes Apex (<hi>vz. to the foreſaid</hi> 27 <hi>degr.</hi> 58 <hi>min. of</hi> ♊) and there labell to the ☉, ſo ſhall you ſee in the houre circle <hi>(ſome</hi> 10 <hi>min. after</hi> 8 <hi>of clocke at night)</hi> the houre of Sunne-ſet: and the ſpace of houres numbered betweene Sunne-riſing and ſetting (<hi>being</hi> 16 <hi>houres</hi> ⅓) is the length of the day, and thoſe (16 ⅓ <hi>houres</hi>) take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> out of 24 houres, leaueth (7 ⅔ <hi>houres</hi>) the length of the night. Alſo the houre of Sunne ſet (<hi>vz</hi> 8 ⅙ doubled any day, maketh (16 ⅓ <hi>houres</hi>) the iuſt length of the day as before. And heere alſo if you labell to the Weſt point of the houre circle, it ſhall ſhew you in the Celeſtialls limbe (118 <hi>deg.</hi> 30 <hi>mi.</hi>) the oblique deſcencion (<hi>in the ſaid</hi> 51 <hi>lati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude</hi>) As for the difference of deſcencion, it is all one with the difference of aſcencion.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:4837:21"/>
               <p>This Chapter is moſt eaſily to be performed by the parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular moouer in the 1 Cap. mentioned: For if you mooue it about leftwards (<hi>vz.</hi> from Weſt towards Eaſt, according to <hi>Copernicus Hipotheſis,</hi> and contrary to all other Aſtrolabes) till the Eaſt part of the particular <hi>Horizon</hi> come to the Sunne, the Labell layd thereon, ſheweth the houre of riſing, and continuing that moouing till the Weſter part of the <hi>Horizon</hi> come to the Sunne, the Labell there applyed, ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the Sunne ſetting: yea, and more then that, the Labell there at both places ſheweth the amplitude of the Sunne ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing and ſetting, by the proſpectiue degrees of the <hi>Horizon.</hi> Note, that if you would be curious, you ſhould at Sunne ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing apply the Labell a quarter of a degree ſhort, and for the Sunne ſetting a quarter of a degree further on in the-clip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticke, then the Sunnes Apex is planted in regard of the Sunnes diurnall motion, being euery 24 houres almoſt a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, for that the Apex is ſet but iuſt for noone, the reaſon whereof is ſhewed in the 6. Cap. Note alſo, that for the riſing and ſetting of Starres, and the other Planets, they are to be done by the particular in all reſpects as for the Sunne, ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing that you muſt remember <hi>ſemper locus ſolis oſtendit horam:</hi> Alſo, the getting of the aſſencions and deſcencions haue all one working with the generall.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="chapter">
               <head>Cap. 18. ¶ To know the houre of riſing or ſetting of any other Starre, Planet, or point in the Heauens, and their diurnall and nocturnall arches, and their oblique aſſencions and difference of aſſencion in any Countrey.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N all theſe caſes where we intreate of the houre, it is intended that the Sunnes place is ſet by the 3. Cap. (<hi>admit at</hi> 26 <hi>degr.</hi> 3 <hi>min. in Piſces, for the</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4837:21"/> 5 <hi>day of March</hi> 1598.) Now to knowe the time of riſing or ſetting of any Planet, Starre, or point propoſed <hi>(admit the great Starre Arcturus)</hi> for any time and place propoſed, you ſhall prepare the Almicantifer to the Horizon propoſed in all reſpects as in the laſt Cap. you did (<hi>vz. the Curſor planted vnto the outermoſt end of the</hi> 51 ⅔ <hi>Zenith line, and the poin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter vnto the</hi> 51 ⅔ <hi>Horizontall point ſeruing with vs heere at Reading.</hi>) And then for the time of riſing, you muſt let the <hi>Almicantifer</hi> play on the Eaſt Hemicicle, and there apply the pointer to the centre of <hi>(Arcturus)</hi> the Starre or point propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and there holding faſt the <hi>Zenitfer,</hi> labell to the Sunne, ſo ſhall you finde cut in the houre circle (<hi>about</hi> 20 <hi>min. paſt</hi> 6 <hi>of clocke in the afternoone</hi>) the houre and time of his riſing. And there alſo if you labell to the Eaſt point of the houre-circle, it ſheweth in the limbe of the Celeſtiall (280 ⅓ <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees</hi>) the oblique aſcencion of the ſame Starre or point <hi>(Arcturus)</hi> in the (51 ⅔) latitude propoſed, which taken out of the right aſcencion (209 ⅓) had by the 8 Cap. leaueth (19 <hi>degrees</hi>) the difference. Note, that if happily you thinke your houre circle with the ſmalleſt to direct you to the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique aſcencion exactly when you lay the Labell on the Eaſt or Weſt points, know that he muſt cut the like part of the Degree where he lighteth as the noone-line or North-line do in the degrees where they are. Note alſo, that to knowe the oblique aſcencion, is as much to ſay, as to know what d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gree of the <hi>Aequinoctiall</hi> doth riſe with any Starre or Planet on any oblique <hi>Horizon.</hi> As for the houre of ſetting, let the <hi>Almicantifer</hi> prepared as before, play on the Weſt He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>micicle, and aply the pointer there againe on the ſaid Starre <hi>(Arcturus)</hi> or point propoſed, where if you labell to the Sunne (<hi>at</hi> 26 <hi>degrees</hi> 3 <hi>min. in</hi> ♓,) it ſhall ſhewe you in the houre-circle (20 <hi>min. paſt</hi> 10 <hi>the next morning</hi>) the time of his ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting: and the houres reckoned on the houre-circle betweene his time of riſing and ſetting (<hi>being</hi> 16) is his diurnall arch, which taken out of 24, leaueth (8 <hi>houres</hi>) his nocturnall arch.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:4837:22"/>
               <head>Cap. 19. ¶ How to ſet perticular degrees on the Almican<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifer, for any perticular latitude.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Do not ſtand making ſpeciall Chapters of the vſe of the perticular moouer in the 1 Cap. mentioned, becauſe it conſiſteth but of the very ſame Horizon circle and 12 hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of one perticular latitude, which old 1 <hi>Stophlerus,</hi> and our old engliſh Laureat <hi>G. Chaucer,</hi> haue ſo largely and plainely written of: withall, being a thing moſt commonly in vſe, and differing in no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, but that they according to the auncient Aſtronomers, appointed the Starry Heauens to mooue rightwards from Eaſt towards Weſt, vppon the earth or fixed Horizon of the place. And I according to <hi>Copernicus</hi> cauſe the earth or Horizon to moue leftwards from Weſt towards Eaſt, vppon the Starry Firmament fixed: In ſo much, that if in this my Aſtrolabe you hold ſtill that perticular moouer with one hand, and with your vnder hand turne about the Celeſtiall, then is it iumpe <hi>Stophler</hi> againe. In which motion (a pretty thing to note) one that ſtandeth by ſhall hardly perceiue any other but that the Reete mooueth, although in deede you turne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the Mater, ſtrongly confirming <hi>Copernicus</hi> Argument, who ſayth, that the weakeneſſe of our ſenſes do imagine the Heauens to mooue about euery 24 houres from Eaſt to Weſt by a <hi>Primum mobile,</hi> where as in deede they haue been alwayes fixed, and it is the earth that whirleth about euery 24 houres from Weſt to Eaſt, of his owne propper nature allotted vnto him, as moſt fit for the receptacle of all tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitory things, being appointed in a place where nothing is to ſtay him from his continuall moouing: but of thoſe things I haue more iuſt occaſion to intreate of in my <hi>Organum V<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranicum</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4837:22"/> very ſhortly to come foorth. But now if the ſayd particular moouer ſhould alſo haue his perticular Almican<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tares like the Reete of my Iewell tediouſly cut out, they would much obſcure this faire face of the Celeſtiall, very needleſſe: becauſe the perticular Zenith-line of the place, with his 90 rootes annexed to the noone-line for the Curſor to play vppon, and the perticular degrees by this Cap. pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared on the Almicantifer, ſhall ſerue in all reſpects as well or rather better. And the manner of preparing them is in a manner already ſet downe in the 13 Cap. Yet is it more eaſily to be done by a perticular, whoſe radyall degrees on the North line, which before I haue tearmed North degrees, are or ſhould be ready numbered from the Horizontall point, towards the Verticall point, ending there at 90 degrees, which in the generall can not be ſuffered. Wherefore kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping the fiduciall line of the Almicantifer euen with the North line, then ſliding the Curſor from roote to roote of the 90 rootes of your perticular Zenith line, ſet nickes in the Almicantifer at euery degree, from degree to degree of the 90 North degrees, numbered from the Horizontall point, towards the Verticall point, correſpondent to each roote as they paſſe in order, till the whole 90 particular degrees be in manner as in the 13 Cap. is ſhewed by thoſe nicks placed on the Almicantifer, and then diſtinguiſh them by tennes, and ſet numbers vnto them accordingly, ſo are they very ready for diuers ſpeciall purpoſes in one latitude, and if neede were, a man may by the two edges on both faces ſet the like in for foure latitudes, and thoſe will neere be ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient for any one region or prouince, or elſe he might haue it made with ſome chanell to receiue a ſlip of velome or paſte-boorde, whereon with pen and inke ſpeedily to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare it for any latitude.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:4837:23"/>
               <head>Cap. 20. ¶ How to know the amplitude of the riſing or ſetting of the Sunne or Starres.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE true Eaſt and Weſt points of any Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rizon are the Interſections of the Equinoc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall therewith: and that is the cauſe why in deſcribing the generall Horizons, they make them all to meete at two points which are thoſe, and for that cauſe it is manifeſt, that there can no Planet, Starre, or point of the heauens, riſe or ſet directly in the true Eaſt or Weſt points of any Horizon, but only ſuch as are ſcituate for the time being in the <hi>Aeq<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noctiall</hi> circle. Wherefore thoſe that are North from the Equinoctiall, muſt needes riſe and ſet Northwards from the true Eaſt and Weſt points, and thoſe that are Southwards<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> riſe and ſet Southwards, and that more or leſſe, according to their diſtaunce, and the obliquitie of the Horizon propoſed. And the degrees of the Horizon circle betweene the true Eaſt and Weſt points, and their riſing and ſetting, are called the amplitude of riſing and ſetting, which in the perticular moo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer are immediately ſeene by the degrees of the Horizon circle, as in the 17 Cap is ſayd: but by the generall it aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth a little paines in this manner. Get the oblique aſcencion of the Sunne, Starre, or point propoſed for the time and place<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> by the 17 or 18 Cap. <hi>(which for the Sunne was in the Horizon of Plymouth the day of the proſperous ſetting foorth of our ſaide noble Lords, founde in the</hi> 17 <hi>Cap.</hi> 56 <hi>degrees</hi> 20 <hi>minutes of the Celeſtialls limbe,)</hi> and thereto apply the noone-line, and there hold the Zenithfer fixed: where it you haue the Almicantif<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r by the laſt Cap prepared for the firſt latitude, <hi>vz.</hi> vnto the Zenith line, neereſt vnto the noone-line,
<pb facs="tcp:4837:23"/> whoſe Horizontall point is in the centre of the Aſtrolabe, and then running the Curſor downe by the rootes of the ſame firſt Zenith line, keeping the fiduciall line of the Almicantifer ſtill on the Sunne, Starre, or point propoſed, vntill the Curſor among the rootes, and the ☉ or Starre among the prepared degrees doe cut like number, for then is the complement thereof, the degrees of the amplitude ſought. But if your Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>micantifer be not prepared, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n muſt you prepare him and his pointer as in the 13 Cap. is taught, firſt to one degree of altitude, then to another, making ſtill proffers to the ☉ or Starre, till the pointer touch vppon it, (<hi>which will fall out at</hi> 41 <hi>degrees of that firſt Zenith line and latitude</hi>) and the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees ſo found, taken out of 90, leaueth (49 <hi>degrees</hi>) the am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plitude (<hi>of the</hi> ☉) ſought.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="chapter">
               <head>Cap. 21. ¶ To know what Starres do neuer riſe or ſet in any latitude, and which do once a day touch the Zenith point, or the Horizontall point.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His matter is moſt eaſy, (your Verticall point and Horizontall point choſen by the 10 Cap.) to be done by the bare moouing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout of the Zenitfer, for in that motion, ſuch Starres <hi>(as the tayle of Vrſa maior, and the head of Perſeus, and ſuch like)</hi> as touch the Verticall point be ſure (<hi>in our</hi> 51 ⅔ <hi>latit. heere at Reading</hi>) do come once in 24 houres to the Zenith of that place: And ſuch as do not reach vnto the (51 ⅔) Horizontall point, (<hi>as all Vrſa maior but</hi> 2 <hi>Starres Vrſa minor, Caſſiopeia, Cepheus &amp;c</hi>) do n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uer et<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> And ſuch as touch vppon the Horizontall point, <hi>(as Caput Me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>ſe lucida lyre, the ring of Andromedaes cheine &amp;c.)</hi> do once in 24 houres touch vppon the Horizon of
<pb facs="tcp:4837:24"/> the (51 ⅔) latitude propoſed, yet do not ſet vnder it. By the particular moouer, theſe things are moſt plainely percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, and reddily done by the moouing of the Horizon circle about.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="chapter">
               <head>Cap. 22. ¶ To know any day and houre what Starres or points in the Heauens are in or neere the Meridian, or do riſe or ſet in any Latitude.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His matter is as eaſy as the laſt. Labell the Sunne (<hi>admit placed at</hi> 20 <hi>degrees</hi> 10 <hi>min. in</hi> ♎ <hi>for the</hi> 2. <hi>of October</hi> 1596) to any houre in the houre circle (<hi>admit to</hi> 8 <hi>of clock at night</hi>) and ſo ſhall the noone-line of the Zenitfer ſhew <hi>(the two Starres, called Caude Capricorni, and Lucida Hidri, but a little paſt, &amp;c.)</hi> ſuch Starres as are the ſame inſtant in the South, and the 12 degree of <hi>Aquarius</hi> in the <hi>medium Celi</hi> vnder the noone-line. And there holding faſt the Zenitfer, being prepared vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Horizon (51 ⅔ <hi>heere at Reading</hi>) propoſed, leade the Almicantifer about the Eaſt Hemiſpheare, and looke what Starres <hi>(as part of Perſeus, one of the heads of</hi> ♊, <hi>the Bulles head, the ſinne of the Whale, &amp;c.)</hi> you ſhall finde the poin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to touch vppon: the ſame aſſuredly, do euen that moment emerge and riſe on the Horizon. That done, the Zenitfer ſtill remayning and prepared to the Horiſon as before, leade the Almicantifer about the Weſt Hemiſpheare, and you ſhall finde the pointer to touch vppon ſuch Starres <hi>(vz. one in the arme pit, another in the bowe of</hi> ♐, <hi>&amp;c.)</hi> as are euen then ready to ſet and go downe vnder the Horizon. This is alſo moſt eaſy by the Horizon circle of the particular, which being but ſet to the houre, the Starres riſing appeare in the Eaſt Hemiſpheare, and thoſe ſetting: in the Weſt and thoſe in the Meridian: vnder the noone-line.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="23" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:4837:24"/>
               <head>Cap. 23. ¶ How to know the houre diſtance of any Planet, Starre, or point of the Heauens from the Meridian, any day and yeare pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, and in any latitude.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat is to ſay, how many houres any Planet, Starre, or point <hi>(admit oculus Tauri)</hi> not being in the South at any time aſſigned, (<hi>admit at</hi> 10 <hi>of clocke at night the</hi> 5 <hi>of March</hi> 1598.) will be before he come to the Meridian of any place (<hi>admit our Meridian heere at Reading in the</hi> 51 ⅔ <hi>latitude</hi>) propoſed, or if he be paſt, how many houres he is paſt: You ſhall labell the houre giuen in the houre-circle (<hi>vz.</hi> 10 <hi>of clocke at night</hi>) to the ☉ planted as in the 3 Cap. (<hi>at</hi> 26 <hi>degr.</hi> 3 <hi>min. of</hi> ♓) there holde faſt the Zenitfer, and labell to your Starre <hi>(oculus Tauri)</hi> or point propoſed, ſo doth the labell ſhew in the houre-circle (<hi>fiue houres</hi> ⅔ <hi>almoſt Weſtwards, and therefore paſt the Meridian</hi>) the houre and part that the Starre or point is diſtant, which if it be on the Eaſt part, then is not that Starre or point come to the Meridian, if Weſtwards <hi>(as heere it was)</hi> then is he paſt the Meridian (5 ⅔ <hi>houres</hi>) ſo many houres.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="24" type="chapter">
               <head>Cap. 24. ¶ How to know the height of the Sunne, or of any other Planet or Starre, for any houre of the day any yeare in any latitude.</head>
               <p>SEeke your houre propoſed (<hi>admit</hi> 10 <hi>of clock in the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the</hi> 2 <hi>of Octob.</hi> 1596 <hi>in our</hi> 51 ⅔ <hi>lati.</hi>) in the houre-circle, &amp; labell it to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Suns carect (<hi>at</hi> 20 <hi>d.</hi> 10 <hi>mi. in</hi> ♎)
<pb facs="tcp:4837:25"/> there hold the Zenitfer faſt. Now if the particular degrees be planted on the Almicantifer, as in the 19 Cap. is taught, you ſhall, (keeping the fiduciall line of the Almicantifer on the Starre or Sonnes Apex,) neede but to ſlide the Curſor too and fro on the Zenith line of the (51 ⅔) latitude propoſed, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till the Curſor among the rootes of that (51 ⅔) Z<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nith-line, and the Sunnes Apex or centre of the Starre (<hi>admit of ocu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus</hi> ♉) among the particular degrees of the Almicantifer, do cut like number, (<hi>which you ſhall finde for the</hi> ☉ <hi>to be at the</hi> 25 <hi>roote, and</hi> 25 <hi>particular degrees, and for oculus tauri at the</hi> 3 ½ <hi>roote, and</hi> 3 ½ <hi>particular degrees,</hi>) for thoſe ſhall be the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees of the Sunne or Starres altitude ſought. But if your Almicantifer haue not the particular degrees, then muſt you as in the 13 Cap. is taught, prepare it to ſome degree at a venture, and make a proffer to the Sunne or Starre, to ſee if the pointer will touch it: if it do not, prepare it againe and againe if neede be, further off, or neerer, as the cauſe requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth, till it do hit, as in the 20 Cap. you did, which with a very little practiſe will be as eaſy as the particular. This and the 20 are the onely two hardeſt in the booke, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſpare not ſo little paines as they require.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="25" type="chapter">
               <head>Cap. 25. ¶ How you ſhall moſt eaſily learne to know all the Conſtellations and Starres in the element it ſelfe.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">E</seg>Ven as a lofe of dowe or paſte, after it is new moulden round and copped, if you then put it into a preſſe, will become a flat cake: Euen ſuch a cake made of the round Spheare or Globe preſſed, is the Celeſtiall of our new Aſtrolabe, which I would haue you now for this purpoſe imagine to be a lofe or round Globe againe: and that euery of his circles
<pb facs="tcp:4837:25"/> had their due conuexities in ſuch ſort, that a little pretty fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe like <hi>Tom Thumbe</hi> might eaſily ſeate himſelfe vnder them as vnder a Canapy in the very centre of the concauity, with this conceite, if at any houre of any night giuen (<hi>admit at</hi> 10 <hi>of clocke at night the ſaide</hi> 5 <hi>of March</hi> 1598) you hauing firſt placed that houre of the houre-circle vnto the Sunnes Carect placed by the 3 Cap. (<hi>vnto</hi> 26 <hi>degr.</hi> 3 <hi>min. of</hi> ♓,) there faſtning the Zenithfer: And then going abroade, by help of your Meridian ſet, as in the 9 Cap. do place your Aſtrolabe flat on ſome ſtoole, plaine leuell with the Horizon, with his noone-line directed towards the South, euen with the ſaide Meridian line, and the North line towardes the North. Then with a priuy ſkonce and candle, one while viewing your Aſtrolabe, another while hiding the light, and viewing the element, you ſhall ſoone perceiue all the Starres of any conſtellacion in the heauens which are then aboue your Horizon, in the like proportion one from another, and differing in their magnitudes, as in the Celeſtiall they are deſcribed: in ſo much, that your little pretty fellow ſitting in the centre vnder this conceited canapy of Starres and ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, if it were tranſparent as glaſſe or cryſtall, ſhould there plainely ſee the Starres in the element, each anſwering his match in this canapy, by the viſuall lines from his eye, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially if the noone-line be eleuated according to the Equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noctialls height, or latitudes complement, becauſe the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectment is polare.</p>
               <p>But if this do not ſatiſfye you ſufficiently, then is beſt for you hauing placed your Zenitfer as before by the houre propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, to ſee by the 22 Cap. what Starres are vnder or neere the noone-line, and of which magnitude they are, (<hi>you ſhall finde at</hi> 10 <hi>of clocke the</hi> 5 <hi>of March</hi> 1598 <hi>the great Starre of the firſt magnit. in the breſt of the Lyon, called Cor Leo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis, directly vnder it, and the bright Starre of Hydra of the</hi> 2 <hi>magnitude not much paſt</hi>) and by the 16 Cap. learne their meridian altitude (<hi>which for Cor Leonis, you ſhall by the</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4837:26"/> 16 <hi>Cap. finde</hi> 52 <hi>degrees, and for lucida hidri</hi> 33 <hi>degrees,</hi>) which had, go foorth with an Aſtrolabe or Quadrant with his fightes ſet to that altitude directly towards the South, and you ſhall wellneere finde your Starres deſired euen with your ſight holes, and you be not too long about it. Alſo at any time you may lay the noone-line to any Starre <hi>(admit Arctu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus)</hi> you deſire to know, and then labell to any houre of the night propoſed, (<hi>admit</hi> 10 <hi>of clocke</hi>) then marke what de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of the clipticke the labell there cutteth, (<hi>you ſhall finde</hi> 1 <hi>degr.</hi> 30 <hi>min. in</hi> ♊) and ſeeke by the 5 Cap. what moneth and day thereof that the Sunne commeth to that degree, (<hi>you ſhall finde on the</hi> 12 <hi>day of May anno</hi> 1598) for on that day be ſure to finde that Starre in the South at 10 of clock at night, where you may make triall of his Meridian altitude as before. And hauing thus or any other way attained the perfect knowledge of ſome fewe, you ſhall eaſily by them de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcrye the reſt by their ſcituation vnto them, and imagined diſtaunces to others, ſome being in ſtreight lines from two other, ſome making a triangular, ſome a quadrangular forme of ſundry ſhapes: And this ſhall ſuffice an ingenious conceit in a fewe nightes to learne to know moſt of the conſtellacions and their Starres, who ſhall the whiles finde the time ſpent in heauenly pleaſure and delightes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="26" type="chapter">
               <head>Cap. 26. ¶ Of the 4 Cardines, and the ſundry riſing and ſetting of the fixed Starres with the Planets.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Meridian and Horizon of euery place do alwayes croſſe each other in halfe on the North and South points of the ſame Hori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zon: which croſſing, maketh of thoſe two circles 4 ſemicircles, which are called the 4 <hi>Cardines.</hi> Vnto either of which when any
<pb facs="tcp:4837:26"/> Planet commeth, eſpecially if he be accompanyed or ſtrongly aſpected with ſome other forcible Planet, Starre, or conſtel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lacion, he worketh ſpeciall effects, whether it be in natiuities or other cauſes, eſpecially at any ſuch time, looke aſſuredly for ſome preſent alteracion of the weather in that Horizon, becauſe there they do ſtrongly affect and aſpect the aſcendent Horizon and Climat, either by coniunction, oppoſition, or quartile, which are the ſtrongeſt: the other, as the <g ref="char:trine">△</g> and ⚹, are counted of leſſe force. And whoſoeuer will take vpon him to iudge of Aſpects or Eclipſes, if he haue not an eye whether they aſpect the Climat, or to iudge of the weather, and not ſpecially regard the effects of the fixed Starres with the Planets, ſhall finde it to prooue but loſt labour, and happily be counted a common lyar, as ſome of our vnſkilfull Progno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticators are, and the reſt little better thought of, becauſe of their negligence or ignorance. But to come to my purpoſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, you ſhall vnderſtand, that when any Starre riſeth together with any Planet on the Horizon (if with the ☉, then is it called the <hi>Coſmicall riſing</hi> and if ſetting at Sunne ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the <hi>Coſmicall ſetting,</hi> if riſing the Sunne ſetting, the <hi>Acronicall riſing,</hi> if ſetting with the ☉, the <hi>Acronicall ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting.</hi>) The Coſmicall riſing is eaſily knowne by applying the Almicantifer prepared to the Horizon vnto any Planet in the Eaſt Hemicicle: there hold faſt the Zenitfer, and play a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the Almicantifer, and looke what Starres the pointer toucheth on in the Eaſt Hemicicle, be ſure thoſe do riſe at the ſame time Coſmically with that Planet, and thoſe he toucheth on in the Weſt Hemicicle, do then Coſmically ſet with the ſame Planet, then riſing. Likewiſe, if you put ouer the Almicantifer ſo prepared, cauſing the Planet to lye in the Eaſt Hemicicle, applying the pointer there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, and there holding faſt the Zenitfer, do leade the Almi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cantifer about, then be ſure that ſuch Starres as the poin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter lighteth on in the Eaſt Hemicicle, ſhall riſe acronically with that Planet ſetting, and thoſe in the Weſt Hemicicle,
<pb facs="tcp:4837:27"/> ſhall ſet acronically together with the Planet ſetting: and what time of the yeare any of theſe ſhall happen, is eaſily con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued by that hath been ſaid in the laſt Cap. and elſewhere: For vnto the Starre propoſed, if you apply the pointer prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to the Horizon, &amp; there holding the Zenithfer, do remooue the Almicantifer till the pointer touch or cut the Clipticke either in the Eaſt or Weſt Hemicicle. Then by the <hi>Ephe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer.</hi> or my <hi>Vranicum</hi> you may eaſily know when &amp; what day any Planet ſhal come vnto thoſe points of the-cliptick ſo cut, and the degree of the ☉ for that day alſo labelled, ſheweth there in the houre-circle the houre of the day (the Zenitfer be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing neuer ſtirred all the while) when any ſuch riſing or ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting ſhall happen.</p>
               <p>For example, this yeare 1596 ſome 5 or 6 dayes together before the end of September, after long ſitting all day wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting this preſent booke, I was in the euenings hindred of my recreating walks by ſodaine riſing of the winde with ſhowres of raine, though the dayes were reaſonable faire, I therefore ſought this my new Aſtrolabe, and found the <hi>Pleiades</hi> or 7 Starres to riſe in the euenings coſmically with <hi>Iupiter,</hi> being retrograde all the while, ♀ alſo being then retrograde, for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trogradacion cauſeth rayne, eſpecially in ☿ without all fayle more or leſſe as he ſhall be affected or aſpected. Alſo the 2 of October 1596 I was ſodeinly ouertaken riding from <hi>Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding</hi> to my poore houſe at <hi>Swallowfeild</hi> at euen, with a moſt ſtormy rayne that continued an houre or two after very ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treame, it made me looke my Aſtrolabe againe, where I found <hi>ſpica virguis</hi> the Sunne ♂ and ☿ had ſet all together acroni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally within one halfe houre or leſſe that this ſtorme began, and then an houre after that <hi>Iupiter</hi> was to riſe as before coſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mically with the <hi>Pleyades.</hi> Now I leaue it to our ſufficient Prognoſticators to iudge whether theſe might be efficient cauſes ſufficient or no, and do commend this my Aſtrolabe vnto them as a moſt needfull thing for them, wiſhing them to haue a ſpeciall regard of the riſing, ſetting, and culminating
<pb facs="tcp:4837:27"/> of the fixed Starres. The common countreyman ſeeing any day inclined to moyſture, can ſay, that it will ſurely rayne when the Sunne and the winde come together, neither will it indeede rayne till then for the moſt part, how likely ſo euer. And wherefore then ſhould not we beleeue the learned, that affirme the riſing of <hi>Orion, Arcturus, Corona, &amp;c.</hi> to prouoke tempeſtious weather, the Kid and Goate windes, the <hi>Hiades, Pleiades</hi> and <hi>Succule</hi> rayne, and eſpecially happening with any forcible Planet or ſtrong aſpect, the more violent. Were it not for conſuming the time, I could recite examples of all theſe and diuers other that I haue vpon like occaſions noted to my ſelfe, but dare preſume no further, leaſt I ſhould be billed amongſt the common liers, as others are happily cauſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe: for no doubt the Almighty hath the raigne in his hand, to alter all at his pleaſure when they haue all done their beſt. Yet that which is moſt to be condemned in them is, that they agree ſeldome in one coniecture, which muſt needes bewray ſhamefull ignorance in ſome of them at the leaſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="27" type="chapter">
               <head>Cap. 27. ¶ Of the 12 houſes, and ſetting the Figure.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Earned men conſidering the Sunne not only at his comming vnto the 4 chiefe points of the-clip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticke, <hi>vz.</hi> the two Equinoctiall and the two Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitiall points, to cauſe the Spring, <hi>Autumne,</hi> Sommer and Winter, but alſo that in euery other of the 12 Signes he maketh ſome alteration of the yeare and ſeaſons. Euen ſo, finding ſuch ſpeciall effects to happen by the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of the Planets vnto the 4 <hi>Cardines,</hi> either with the fixed Starres or without, as in the laſt Cap. is touched, they did imagine that the Planets and Starres might haue alſo ſome forces and effects in other meane places betweene: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore tooke vpon them to adde 8 ſemicircles more vnto the 4
<pb facs="tcp:4837:28"/> 
                  <hi>Cardines,</hi> croſſing with them at the two meridian Horizontall points, making vp the number of 12, which they call the 12 houſes. Thoſe on the particular moouer are ready drawne, ſo that applying but the houre in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moouers limbe to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Sunne, your Figure is ſet immediately and moſt excellently by this Aſtrolabe, fully fraught with all his needfull tackling, <hi>his Lords, termes, faces, triplicities, aſpects, Planets and Starres in their places, natures of the</hi> 12 <hi>houſes, and of the</hi> 12 <hi>Signes, the gradus maſculini, feminini, lucidi, tenebrofi, vacui, fumo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſi, &amp;c.</hi> and what not? appertaining to the Iudiciary arte, as if you reade <hi>Alkabitius, Claud. Dariotus</hi> which is engliſhed, <hi>Gwydo Bonatus,</hi> and others their introductions to that arte, comparing the 2 Cap. therewithall, you will eaſily conceiue.</p>
               <p>But to finde theſe 12 houſes in any countrey <hi>(admit heere at Reading)</hi> by the generall for any day and yeare propoſed, (<hi>admit at</hi> 10 <hi>of clocke the</hi> 5 <hi>day of March</hi> 1598) you ſhall labell the houre propoſed (<hi>vz.</hi> 10 <hi>of the clocke</hi>) ſought in the houre circle vnto the Sunne, placed by the 4. Cap. (<hi>at</hi> 25 <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees</hi> 3. <hi>min. in</hi> ♓) there doth the noone-line ſhew you (22 <hi>degr.</hi> 30 <hi>min. of</hi> ♒) the degree of the-clipticke, beginning the 10 houſe and the North line (22 <hi>degr.</hi> 30 <hi>min. in</hi> ♌) the degree beginning the 4 houſe, where alſo (holding faſt the Zenitfer) play the <hi>Almicantifer</hi> prepared to the (51 ⅔) Hori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zon, on both ſides of the noone-line, ſo ſhall the pointer cut the clipticke in the Eaſt Hemicicle at (28 <hi>degr.</hi> 30 <hi>min. in</hi> ♊) his degree beginning the firſt houſe commonly called the aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent or <hi>Horoſcope,</hi> and in the Weſt Hemicicle at (28 <hi>degr.</hi> 30 <hi>min. in</hi> ♐) the deſcendent or degree beginning the 7 houſe, ſo haue you the 4 <hi>Cardines, Angles,</hi> or principall houſes of any figure in a manner as ready, as by the particular moo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, which (hauing as the common manner is, drawne your <hi>Scheame</hi> or Figure for the 12 houſes) you ſhall plant there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in accordingly.</p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>astrological diagram</figDesc>
                  <head>Fig: Celi 5: Martij Hor: 10 1598</head>
               </figure>
               <p>Note, that if in playing about the <hi>Almicantifer</hi> you chance to meete with any notable fixed Starre any thing neere, it ſhall not do amiſſe to ſet him alſo in your figure. Alſo I am to note vnto you, that there are two things that fall out vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luckily in this practiſe, which you ſhall thus ſalue. The firſt is, that the breadth of the Zenitfer hideth from the pointer the Horizon point ſet at the Apex in the Eaſt Hemicicle. This is ſalued two wayes: the one is, when the Almicantifer is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to ſet the Curſor at ſo many degrees of the North line.
<pb facs="tcp:4837:29"/> as he is at in the Noone line, and ſo will the Eaſt and Weſt points of the houre-circle change their places for the time: The other way generall to all foure remooues of the Zenith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer. For ſo ſoone as you had gotten the 4 Cardines, if you had made in the Celeſtialls limbe on each ſide of the noone-line two markes, the one 30 the other 60 degrees diſtant from it, that ſhall ſerue as well and in ſtead of the foure times, applying of the pointer to the Horizon point before vſed, as if you trye both wayes you ſhall finde, and produce one truth.</p>
               <p>And whereas for diuers latitudes, ſome of the domifying rootes do go out of the Zenitfer, thoſe may eaſily be ſupplyed with help of a threed and pearle added to the pointer, or with helpe of a paire of compaſſes thus: Firſt, caſt away 45 out of your radiall number ſhewed by the ſlope line (<hi>vz. out of the</hi> 57 ⅔ <hi>caſting</hi> 45, <hi>there remaineth</hi> 12 ⅔) and ſet y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Curſor vnto twiſe ſo many of the domifying rootes of the noonelines ſcale as the remaine commeth vnto, (<hi>vz. vnto the</hi> 25 ⅔ <hi>domifying roote</hi>) and there apply the pointer vnto the like number of the domifying radiall degrees of the North line (<hi>vz. vnto</hi> 25 ⅓ <hi>degr. reckoned on the North line from the equinoctials inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſection towards the centre</hi>) and then the Curſor remayning, do apply the fiduciall line of the Almicantifer euen with the fiduciall noone-line of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Zenitfer outwards, there doth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> poin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters Apex ſhew y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> true place of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> roote wanting, where if you pitch one foote of your compaſſe, or faſten a threed, and with the other or with the pearle extended to the domifying ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyall degree of the ſlope line, (<hi>vz. vnto the</hi> 57 ⅔ <hi>radiall domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying degree,</hi>) offer to deſcribe a circle, it ſhall cut the-clip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticke as before the pointer did at 22 degrees of ♓ and of ♍, ſo the noone-line ſtand at his due place as before, <hi>vz.</hi> at 30 or 60 degrees of the Celeſtialls limbe from the firſt conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="28" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:4837:30"/>
               <head>Cap. 28. ¶ Of the aſpects of the Planets, and how to finde them.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here are in Aſtronomy three chiefe cardinall aſpects (as I may tearme them) <hi>vz.</hi> the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iunction marked thus ☌, and is, when as two Planets meete in one degree and minute of longitude. The Oppoſition marked thus ☍, when as they are iuſt ſixe ſignes in ſunder. The Quartile marked thus <g ref="char:quadrine">□</g>, when as they are three ſignes diſtant. Alſo, there are two other of leſſe force, <hi>vz.</hi> the Trine marked thus <g ref="char:trine">△</g>, and is at foure ſignes diſtaunce. And the Sextile marked thus ⚹, at two ſignes diſtaunce. Which aſpects are eaſily deſcryed euen by the very view on this Aſtrolabe, when as the Planets are thereon planted by the 4 Cap. for who can not eſpye quickly when any Planet is coniunct, or 2, 3, 4, or 6 ſignes off from any other, or from any notable fixed Starre. And yet for your better vnderſtanding, I haue from the beginning of ♑ drawne the radiall lines of each aſpect, and ſet the Carecters on them: But now <hi>Alkabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius Bonatus,</hi> and <hi>Dariottus</hi> will tell you, that the Tryne and Sextile are good, the <g ref="char:quadrine">□</g> and ☍ bad, the coniunction of good Planets good, of euill Planets bad, and that the coniunction and ☍ may be allowed ſo long as they are within one degree of another, and the <g ref="char:trine">△</g> 
                  <g ref="char:quadrine">□</g> and ⚹ when they come one within daunger of anothers beames, which for ♄ or ♃ is at 9 degrees before and behinde for ♂ at 8 degrees, ♀ and ☿ at ſeuen, the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> at 12, the ☉ 15 degrees, and ſo farre off their application and ſeparation begnneth and endeth, &amp;c. Alſo <hi>Io. Stophlerus</hi> noteth in this place, <hi>propoſ.</hi> 55. that though a Planet might haue 10 degr. of latitude, yet could it not make 30 min. diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence in the aſpect, and that only in the ⚹ or <g ref="char:trine">△</g> and not to be
<pb facs="tcp:4837:30"/> regarded. Alſo aſpects are ſaid to be dexter aſpects, when the beames proiect in <hi>ſequens</hi> of the-clipticke, and <hi>Siniſter</hi> when in precedens.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="29" type="chapter">
               <head>Cap. 29. ¶ A new deuiſe of the Author to get the Planetary houres in all latitudes, and of their Lords regnant.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hoſe houres which in theſe dayes we call Planetary houres, for that Aſtronomers haue held opinion the Planets to haue their ſeuerall dominions in euery of them, haue beene ſometime called <hi>Horae inequales,</hi> and <hi>Horae temporariae.</hi> Their nature is to diuide euery naturall day betweene Sunne-riſing and ſetting into 12 equall partes, and euery naturall night into other 12. But becauſe in all oblique <hi>Horizons</hi> the dayes and nightes lengthen and ſhorten with the Sommer and Winter, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore theſe houres growing great and leſſe according to the time and latitude, are called <hi>Inequales</hi> and <hi>Temporariae,</hi> they are numbered in the day time from Sunne-riſing, ending at Sunne-ſet with 12, and there the houres of the night begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, do end the next morrow at Sunne-riſing with 12.</p>
               <p>Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſe houres are moſt eaſily had by a ſpeciall Inſtrument called <hi>Horarium Planetarium,</hi> which I my ſelfe haue newly deuiſed, generall to all <hi>Horizons,</hi> which was neuer done be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore me that I haue ſeene, and placed it at the top of the Cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiall, comprehended in the Sextans of a circle, whoſe arche containeth the houres of Sunne-riſing and ſetting, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, it is filled with a number of ſtreight lines, all parallell to the baſe of the Sextans, repreſenting the common, equall, and vſuall houres either of day or night, which are numbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red on the Sextans ſide downewards to 12, for the houres going before the ſixt Planetary houre, and thenſe backe
<pb facs="tcp:4837:31"/> againe outwards for the houres after. And it muſt haue ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding on his Centre a Labell or Scale of the Planetary houres of equall length to the ſide or baſe, deuided into ſixe equall parts, numbered from the outer end inwards, ending at the Centre with 6, and thenſe backe againe, ending at 12 where it began. This Labell or Index is alſo numbered from the Centre outwards vnto 12 for the vſe of the 7 Cap. Now when the common houre of any day or night is giuen, <hi>(admit</hi> 10 <hi>of clocke</hi> 40 <hi>minutes afternoone the</hi> 12 <hi>of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cember</hi> 1583, <hi>being the houre of the natiuity of my neere kinſeman Maiſter Walter Seint-Iohn, ſonne and heyre to Sir Iohn Seint-Iohn Knight of Lyddiard in the County of Willſhire deceaſed)</hi> and that you would know the Planetary houre, you ſhall by the 17 Cap. firſt get the houre and minute of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Sunne ſetting that day, if the houre giuen be of the day or of the Sunne riſing, if the queſtion <hi>(as that natiuity was)</hi> be of the night <hi>(vz. you ſhall finde it about</hi> 8 ¼ <hi>of clocke in the morning)</hi> and vnto that houre (<hi>vz.</hi> 8 ¼) ſought in the <hi>Sextans</hi> arche, ſet the fiduciall line of the Planetary Scale, where immediately you ſhall ſee the houre-line equall to your houre giuen <hi>(vz. the</hi> 10 ⅔ <hi>houre-line reckoned in the Sextans ſide inwards for that midnight will be the</hi> 6 <hi>Plane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary houre)</hi> to cut off in the Planetary Scale the Planetary houre deſired. <hi>(vz. it ſhall cut</hi> ⅔ <hi>partes of the</hi> 9 <hi>Planetary houre.)</hi> And if now you deſire to knowe what Planet bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth dominion that houre, reſort vnto the domineering Table which I haue placed at the lower corner of the Celeſtiall, and therein ſeeke the day or night of the weeke propoſed, accounting Sunday for the firſt, Munday the ſecond, &amp;c. wherein your houre was giuen, <hi>(vz. Thurſday night being the</hi> 5 <hi>night I ſeeke the figure</hi> 5 <hi>by the title (Noctes)</hi> and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low that range of Carects vntill you come vnder your Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netary houre founde, (<hi>vz. vnder the houre figure of</hi> 9) and there ſhall you finde ♄ the Planet domineering that houre.</p>
               <p>Note, that if you had no domineering Table, you might
<pb facs="tcp:4837:31"/> eaſily make it by hart, beginning the firſt houre on Sunday with the ☉, and then reckoning the Planets on your fingers ends thus, ☉, ♀, ☿, <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g>, ♄, ♃, ♂. ☉, ♀, ☿, <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g>, ♄, &amp;c. till you haue done 24, ſo ſhall you finde the 25 in this accoumpt to be <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g>, and thereof Munday is called <hi>dies Lune,</hi> and on Tewſday will fall out ♂ if you reckon on, and thereof called <hi>dies Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis,</hi> euen ſo Wenſday, <hi>dies Mercurij,</hi> of ☿, Thurſday <hi>dies Iouis,</hi> of ♃, Friday <hi>dies Veneris,</hi> of ♀, Saterday, <hi>dies Saturni,</hi> of ♄, and all by reaſon of this accoumpt of the 7 Planets.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="30" type="chapter">
               <head>Cap. 30. ¶ How you ſhall knowe to ſet forwards and back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards any of the fixed Starres vnto their true places for any age paſt, or to come.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Haue in the 2 Cap. ſufficiently ſhewed by what meanes the fixed Starres are in ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parance from age to age, forced out of one ſigne and degree into another, through the ſliding backe of the Equinoctiall interſec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions with the-clipticke: preceeding orderly and equally almoſt euery 67 yeares a degree, which is called the <hi>Medius,</hi> or <hi>Aequalis motus preceſſionis ſeu fixarum.</hi> The gate whereof, how much it is in one day, in one yeare, in 4, in 20, in an 100, and in a 1000 yeares, is ſet downe in the firſt columne of the <hi>Tabula Radicalis,</hi> in the left corner of the Celeſtiall. Wherefore if you would knowe where the equall place of any Starre <hi>(admit of Arcturus)</hi> ſhall be any time to come, <hi>(admit for the yeare after Chriſt</hi> 2000 <hi>compleate)</hi> take 1650 (for that all the North Starres are in this Celeſtiall placed and rectifyed for that yeare) out of the yeare propoſed, and by that firſt columne gather the equall motion aunſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable to that remayne. <hi>(vz.</hi> 1650 <hi>taken out of</hi> 2000 <hi>leaueth</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4837:32"/> 350, <hi>for which</hi> 350 <hi>yeares, I take in the ſaid columne the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of one</hi> 100 <hi>yeares three times, and of</hi> 20 <hi>yeares twiſe, and of</hi> 4 <hi>yeares twiſe, and of one yeare twiſe, for that three times</hi> 100, <hi>and twiſe</hi> 20, <hi>and twiſe</hi> 4, <hi>and twiſe one, do make</hi> 350, <hi>and of that collection there amounteth</hi> 4 <hi>deg.</hi> 53 <hi>min. almoſt.)</hi> And ſo much can I ſay that thoſe North Starres will then be gone forwards from their places, where now in the Cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiall they are ſet in regard of their equall motion. But now there is found out by ſkilfull artes-men a certaine librament or ballaicing of the Equinoctiall and the Poles of the world, as the ſtudyed in the Theoricks well knowe, which at one time helpeth forwards this equall motion, and at another time pulleth it backe againe, euen vnto 71 min. or 1 degr. 11 min. all is one, making by that meanes the true motion vne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall. Therefore I haue within the Radicall table placed an inſtrument of my deuiſe to equate the ſame, which conſiſteth (as the Radicall table doth) of two partes, the one for the ablatiue <hi>Aequations,</hi> the other for the <hi>Adiectiue,</hi> each part hauing two limbes ioyning together, the outermoſt carrying the ſayd 71 minutes two wayes for the ballaicing too and fro: the innermoſt being double, in which are written the yeares from Chriſtes birth for 3440 yeares after, numbered from the ✿ twiſe about, for that in ſo many yeares the <hi>Ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>malye</hi> of this ballaicings compleateth twiſe, &amp; therefore that inner limbe is double. Wherefore if now you would knowe this <hi>Aequacion</hi> for any yeare (<hi>admit the yeare</hi> 2000) ſeeke the ſame yeare 2000 in that double limbe, &amp; you ſhall finde in the outer limbe the minutes of equation that anſwere thereunto <hi>(vz. almoſt</hi> 70 <hi>min. ablatiue)</hi> to be added or ſubducted too or from the equall motion before gotten according as the words <hi>Adiectiuae</hi> or <hi>Ablatiuae</hi> do admoniſh. <hi>(vz. whereas the equall motion of the fixed Starres was before found for the yeare af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Chriſt</hi> 2000 <hi>compleate to be gone forwards</hi> 4 <hi>deg.</hi> 53 <hi>mi. you muſt now pull out</hi> 70 <hi>minutes, ſo will there be left</hi> 3 <hi>deg.</hi> 43 <hi>min. their true motion in that</hi> 530 <hi>yeares, according to
<pb facs="tcp:4837:32"/> which, the true place of Arcturus, which for the yeare</hi> 1650 <hi>is placed in this Celeſtiall</hi> 18 <hi>degr.</hi> 55 <hi>min. in ♎, ſhall then be</hi> 22 <hi>degr.</hi> 38 <hi>min in ♎. And ſo for any other North Starre, for they all remooue alike.)</hi> And likewiſe for any of the South Starres, but that you muſt for them worke vpon the yeare 1570, as before you did by 1650. Alſo for any age paſt <hi>(as if it had beene for</hi> 350 <hi>yeares before</hi> 1650. <hi>vz. the yeare after Chriſt</hi> 1300 <hi>compleate)</hi> you ſhould haue found the Equation as much adiectiue, and by that meanes the true motion of 350 yeares backwards 6 degr. 3 min. to be pulled backe from their now place, <hi>(ſo that Arcturus was then but</hi> 12 <hi>degrees</hi> 52 <hi>min. in</hi> ♎.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="31" type="chapter">
               <head>Cap. 31. ¶ How by help of this Aſtrolabe to get the longi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude and latitude of any Planet, yea, or of any Starre or Comet ſeene.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Auing a Meridian exactly ſet as in the 9 Cap. is taught, you ſhall obſerue the comming of any Planet, Starre, or Comet to the Meridian either in the South or North partes, <hi>(as for example the</hi> 2 <hi>of October</hi> 1596 <hi>I obſerued the comming of ♃ to our Meridian heere at Reading)</hi> and there take his meridian altitude <hi>(which I found</hi> 50 ½ <hi>deg.)</hi> as is taught in the 11 Cap. and preſently (except you haue ſome clocke or watch truly ſet) get the houre and minute if you can by taking the altitude of ſome knowne Starre, as in the 13 Cap. is taught, <hi>(I found it a quarter of an houre paſt one and better after midnight)</hi> which done, ſeeke that houre and minute in the houre circle, and labell it to the ☉ planted by the 4 Cap. (<hi>at</hi> 20 <hi>de.</hi> 10 <hi>min. of</hi> ♎) &amp; there hold faſt the Zenitfer, &amp; number the verticall diſtance or complement of the Merid. alti. before-taken <hi>(vz.</hi> 39 ½ <hi>de.)</hi> on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> nooneline fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Zenith point towards <hi>Meridies,</hi> if your Merid. alti. taken were South, or towards
<pb facs="tcp:4837:33"/> 
                  <hi>Media nox,</hi> if North, (<hi>which heere being South, will fall out at the</hi> 12 ¼ <hi>radiall degree numbered from the Aequinoctiall</hi>) where make a pricke on the Celeſtiall, for there ſhall be the true point or place of the (♃) Starre, Planet, or Comet, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued for that inſtant, and the circles of the-clipticks longi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude and latitude cutting that point, ſhall ſhew you his longi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude and latitude ſought (<hi>vz. the circle of longitude paſſing by that verticall diſtance or pricke made, ſhewed me in the clipticke</hi> 8 <hi>degrees</hi> 30 <hi>minutes almoſt of</hi> ♉, <hi>the longitude of</hi> ♃, <hi>and the circle of latitude cutting that pricke, ſhewed me almoſt</hi> 2 <hi>degrees Southwards from the-clipticke his latitude.</hi>) And this ſerueth for the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g>, or any Planet, Starre, or Comet ſeene. And now by helpe of this latitude thus gotten, you may as eaſily get the true places of the Starres ſeene in any other place as well as in the Meridian perpetually, for that their latitudes neuer alter, and of ♄, ♃, or ♂, 20 or 30 dayes af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: for that theirs altereth little in that time, and of ♀ for a day or two after, but not for the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g>, becauſe her latitude chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth ſwiftly, neither for ☿, becauſe in our Clymat we neuer ſee him: In this maner.</p>
               <p>Take the altitude of any Starre, Planet, or Comet, whoſe latitude is foreknowne either by this Cap. or otherwiſe at any houre and minute knowne, taking good heede whether he be in the Eaſt or Weſt Hemiſpheare. Then prepare the Zenitfer to that altitude taken, then labell the houre and minute to the ☉, and there hold faſt the Zenitfer. Which done, apply the pointer to the circle of latitude of the Starre or Planet either in the Eaſt or Weſt Hemicicle, according as the Starre or Planet was at taking his altitude, ſo ſhall the circle of longitude paſſing by the pointer ſo applyed, ſhew the longitude of the Starre or Planet in the-clipticke.</p>
               <p>Note, that <hi>Io. Stophlerus lib.</hi> 2. <hi>prop.</hi> 38. reciteth 7 propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions which ſome lying Aſtronomers (as he tearmeth them) haue taken vpon them to teach on the Aſtrolabe, which he there condemneth to be moſt falſe, and not poſſible, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb facs="tcp:4837:33"/> ſpendeth a Chapter to forewarne euery man to take heede and not to meddle with them. And theſe are the 7, the firſt, to knowe the longitude of the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g>, the ſecond, the longi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of ♄, ♃, ♂, ♀, or ☿, the third, to get their latitudes, the fourth, to know whether a Planet be direct or retrograde, the fift, to know the longitude of any Starre in the Reete, the ſixt, the latitude of fixed Starres, the ſeuenth, the longi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of Starres not in the Reete. And now I am to rewarne all men, that they are all poſſible by this Aſtrolabe, and by my Iewell alſo, and the whole 7 ſauing the 4, are performed by this one Chapter: becauſe I would not haue them now daunted with that 38 <hi>propoſ.</hi> of <hi>Stophler</hi> who meant it no doubt only, by that Aſtrolabe whereof himſelfe wrote.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="32" type="chapter">
               <head>Cap. 32. ¶ A ready way by helpe of this Aſtrolabe, heereafter to obſerue the motions of Comets.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Ecauſe I haue ſeene ſome 4 or fiue yeares paſt a booke entituled <hi>Noua theoria Cometarum</hi> as I remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, ſet foorth by one <hi>Reſlyn,</hi> who taking occaſion vppon that great Comet or Blazing-Starre, which <hi>Anno</hi> 1570 was ſeene ſo long in the Conſtellation of <hi>Caſſiopeia,</hi> in a manner fixed without motion, to imagining therefore that Comet to happen in the very Pole of the <hi>Theoricke,</hi> and that to be the cauſe why he mooued not, thereupon runneth on a courſe, with recitall of diuers Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mets and their motions, but concluded no certaintie to my remembrance, ending his booke with this ſaying, <hi>Eſt quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam prodire tenus ſi non datur vltra.</hi> But our late learned
<pb facs="tcp:4837:34"/> countreyman, Mayſter <hi>Digges,</hi> in his <hi>Scala Mathematica</hi> found, becauſe he had no Parallax, that he muſt needes be beyond the Speere of the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g>. Well no doubt there can not any weighty thing come to perfection at the firſt, ſecond, or third aſſay, and therefore to the end it may be a generall care to obſerue the motions of Comets when they happen, I haue thought good to aduertiſe euery man in this Cap. that either on this Aſtrolabe or on the Globe, it is a moſt eaſy matter when any Planet appeareth, to pricke downe his place euen by the very view of his ſcituation among the fixed Starres, ſeeing by the 25 Cap. before you may ſo eaſily learne to know them all.</p>
               <p>As for example in Iuly this yeare 1596 there appeared a Comet with a ſtreaming tayle vpwards in the North-weſt, which vpon Tewſday the 20 of Iuly aforeſayd, about 9 of the clocke at night, I firſt tooke heede of betweene the two hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der legs of <hi>Vrſa maior</hi> almoſt in a ſtreight line, (but ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what lower, and two parts of the way) between the Starre of the fourth light in the neere hocke of the neere hinder legge, and the two Starres of the third light in the further foote behinde, according whereunto I made a pricke in the Celeſtiall of this Aſtrolabe. The 21 of Iuly the ſame houre, I ſawe him directly in the ſtreight line aforeſayde, and diſtant from the ſayd two Starres twiſe their diſtance. The 22 day the ſame houre I ſawe him a little aboue the ſtreight line, and but their diſtance off. The 23 of Iuly the night was darke. The 24 of Iuly I ſawe him aboue thoſe two Starres of the third light, and to make an equilater triangle with them: all which, I noted downe euery night with pricks, then followed a fewe clowdy and darke nights, and after that 24 day he was no more ſeene. This Comet was ſeene of many others ſome fortnight before I ſawe him, as neere as I could geſſe by their relacion euen about the briſket of <hi>Vrſa maior,</hi> a little behinde the hocke of the neere legge afore, which alſo I pricked downe: and haue cauſed
<pb facs="tcp:4837:34"/> thoſe pricks and the trayle of his gate to be grauen in the Celeſtiall, in the Conſtellacion of <hi>Vrſa maior</hi> if you marke it, (though not done fully to my purpoſe) to the end to incite others heereafter to do the like, that poſterity at the laſt may finde out whether there be any regularity in their motions. If the Comet chaunce to come to the Meridian either in the North or South (as this did not in ſight) then by the laſt Cap. you may get his longitude &amp; latitude euery night, and ſo pricke downe euery dayes motion the more exactly.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
